this is the briefing. i'm samantha simmonds.
our top story: a blueprint for brexit — theresa
may will deliver a long—awaited speech setting
out her plans for a future relationship with
the eu. the misery goes on — heavy snow
and deadly blizzards continue to lash many
parts of europe and will continue into the
weekend. i'm karin giannone, live in the italian
capital, rome, as the last days of campaigning
ahead of sunday's election get underway. there
are plenty of new faces and one very familiar
old one in the ring. and coming up in the
business briefing... raising the temperature.
president trump says he'll slap hefty tariffs
on foreign steel to protect us workers. but
is he playing with fire? we'll be getting
the views of steel workers in pennsylvania
and the reaction on global markets. a warm
welcome to the programme — briefing you
on all
you need to know in global news, business
and sport. and you can be part of the conversation.
with transport chaos all over europe and people
stuck in their cars for hours, we're asking
if we've all been woefully underprepared for
the beast from the east, even though we knew
it was coming. tell us what you think — by
using the hashtag in a few hours, the british
prime minister, theresa may, will set out
her vision for britain's trading relationship
with the european union after brexit. she's
expected to say she wants the "deepest and
broadest possible" agreement, and acknowledge
that some compromises will be necessary. but
she's not expected to change her position
on removing the uk from the customs union.
bill hayton reports.
a shrug of hands and whimsical glance, the
body language of the european council president
after meeting theresa may on thursday wasn't
exactly enthusiastic. donald tusk told her
he wasn't happy with the british government's
red lines, the refusals to be part of the
eu's single market and customs union. in her
speech later on friday she will outline five
tests that any agreement must pass. it must
ensure that britain remains a tolerant, european
democracy and it must strengthen the unity
of the united kingdom. but some brexit supporters
say mrs may needs to go further. we need to
say, right, this is what we're after, we are
reasonable people, we are prepared to compromise,
but unless you're prepared to stop treating
us like a hostage, treat us with some respect,
then we will say that no deal is better than
a bad deal and walk away. however, one veteran
conservative politician, an opponent of brexit,
says that there is far too much to sort out
in such a short time. behind all the passion
about brexit, there are an awful lot of things,
important to our society, important to our
jobs, investment and also our security. and
the environment and other things have to be
sorted out. the eu's brexit negotiator wants
to hear specific proposals from the uk but,
with her own party still deeply divided, mrs
may's speech is more likely to stick to general
principles. we will have more analysis of
the speech coming up on the programme a little
later. heavy snowfall and deadly blizzards
will continue to lash many parts of europe
into the weekend, forcing airports to cancel
or delay
flights and rail services to stop trains around
the continent. the deep freeze has seen the
death toll climb to more than 50 and comes
as some countries now brace for a new round
of storms. virginia langeberg reports. the
snow
storms have seen dozens perishing in freezing
conditions, many of them rough sleepers. in
south—east london man in his 60s died after
falling into frozen pond. it may now be officially
spring but the wintry blizzards continued
to bring highly unusual red weather alert
warnings in parts of the uk. it was hit overnight
by storm emma.
motorists were told to stay off the roads
but that message came too late for thousands
already stranded on motorways. here was one
of the lucky ones. somehow this car and bus
in edinburgh avoided being added to the road
accident statistics. portugal and spain have
been left battered by storm emma and are now
bracing for new storms, expected to bring
up to 75 millimetres of rain by the end of
the weekend. rough seas are already forcing
a offshore oil platform to run aground on
the canary islands. pass operation been left
frozen in time with temperatures plunging
2-23dc in time with temperatures plunging
2—23dc in eastern parts of the country.
—— parts of croatia have been left frozen.
what is a spectacle for some is an inconvenience
for many others. heavy
snowfall has left thousands stranded across
europe from flight and rail cancellations.
this is dublin airport, where flights have
been cancelled until saturday at the earliest.
we're going to have to stay here until saturday.
we're stuck here for two days. i love ireland.
but i'm trying to get out of here. when traditional
modes of transport fail, there will always
be those that improvise. in scotland people
in edinburgh had opted for skis to get around
on foot whilst in aldershot, home of the british
army, still soldiers incorporated a high octane
snowball fight as part of their physical training
session. and you will hardly hear complaints
for children with schools closed because of
the conditions meaning that london parks provided
the perfect wintry playground. perhaps the
only
ones enjoying the wintry cold more, these
baltic seals, in poland, a p pa re ntly these
baltic seals, in poland, apparently unfazed
by their frozen whiskers. and we might as
well settle in and try to cope, because the
cold is sticking around a while longer with
weather warnings remaining in place for the
uk until just after midnight on monday. let's
brief you on some of the other stories making
the news. the catalan separatist leader, carles
puigdemont, says he's ending his bid to be
re—elected president of the spanish region.
but he says the move is only temporary, to
try to break the stalemate with the spanish
authorities. he's been living in self—imposed
exile in belgium since last year's independence
referendum. he faces arrest if he returns.
police in northern france are reopening files
on unsolved rape cases — after a man admitted
carrying out around a0 sex attacks dating
back to the 1990s. french media have named
the suspect as dino scala — a 57 year—old
grandfather and caretaker who was president
of his village football club.
now to our top business story. on his way
to the presidency, the plight of america's
steelworkers was a core theme in donald trump's
message of america first. now he's delivered
on that promise to protect an industry in
decline — announcing steep new tariffs on
steel and aluminium imports next week. the
international response was immediate. canada
described the tariffs as completely unacceptable.
both the european union and china threatened
to retaliate — fuelling fears of a global
trade war. joel kibazo is a partner at jk
associates and a former director of communications
at africa development bank. welcome, good
morning. this announcement seems to have caught
everybody by surprise. announcement seems
to have caught everybody by surpriselj announcement
seems to have caught everybody by surprise.
i think it did. in some ways we should have
expected something like this because president
trump did sort of make these points during
his campaign to become president. but when
you wander was a feeling that some of
that was campaign rhetoric and so would not
cause the much of a trade war plus his party,
the republicans, are the party of free—trade
zone there was an expectation that it would
go ahead in a very mild form. the way it has
happened a stake by surprise. usually there
are leaks and signals before something like
this happens which helps market sort of study.
because it has just come out of the blue,
and we have seen the department of trade,
and the business community in the us was not
prayer “— business community in the us
was not prayer —— was not prepared for
this, so prayer —— was not prepared for
this, so hence the falls we have seen on wall
street and in asian markets. he's talking
about 25% tariff on steel imports and 10%
on aluminium. there has been an angry reaction
from around the world. much of this is aimed
at china. president trump believes that the
trade with china
is unfair, but that's only 2% and actually
the societies that will be at our places like
south korea, one of the main exporters to
the united states, the third biggest after
canada and brazil the united states. above
all that there is also the fa ct above all
that there is also the fact that it will make
things more expensive for consumers. that
is why wall street this falling and markets
are reacting. and joel will be back in about
half an hour to review the main stories being
covered by the global media. stay with us
for that. italians will head to the polls
this sunday to elect a new president. the
race is between three main parties. there's
the centre—right forza italia, headed by
a familiar face — former prime minister
silvio berlusconi. then there's the five star
movement, started star movement, started by
comedian bepe grillo in 2009 and now one of
europe's biggest populist movements. finally
the ruling democratic party led by former
prime minister matteo renzi. well let's cross
live to rome. my colleague karin giannone
is there for us.
good morning to you, karen. good morning,
samantha. italy has been in the grip of final
—— severe winter weather for the final
days of this election campaign. there has
been a lot of noise from the extremes of politics
and as you mentioned there, re—entering
the political stage and reinventing himself
as an elder statesman is a very familiar figure
of 81—year—old silvio berlusconi, but
he is barred from actually holding office
so he is maintaining the campaign from the
sidelines, if you like, but very much centre
stage as well. he can't actually be prime
minister because of a tax fraud conviction
in 2013. let's discuss this more, with me
is the chair of constitutional law at a university
here in rome. 0n the issue of silvio berlusconi,
what exactly can you do? he was convicted
and since there is
a law that provides as a consequence that
he is banned from public office, he has filed
an appeal to the european court of human rights,
but the final decision is not due before fall,
so at this moment that rules him out of the
possibility to hold any office but as you
know, he'sa very hold any office but as you
know, he's a very charismatic leader, so,
asa he's a very charismatic leader, so, as
a political leader from his party, as the
opinion polls show, he is very able to mobilise
the actors and his party is gaining, and there
isa and his party is gaining, and there is
a slight possibility that the right—wing
coalition wins an outright majority on the
day of the election. there is an interesting
factor this time around that the
electoral system is actually a new one. it
is a very complicated. no one. it is a very
complicated. no one is sure how it is going
to work. it is complicated because it is a
mixture of systems. two thirds of it is proportional
in mechanism and the third part is first past
the post. since the italian system, as everybody
knows, is a very fragmented system, it is
very unlikely that some party or some coalition
gets a majority so, if silvio berlusconi is
such a success, it is possible, but not very
likely. then what happens, it is going to
be interesting to see. but what i would rule
out is that the president goes for another
dissolution. there is no tradition of double
dissolution, one following the other. the
possibility is that we restored the negotiation
as it has happened in many countries in europe.
we have to leave it there. we could be seeing
a period of more uncertainty for many weeks
to come. giovanni, thank you. with that, it
is back to you in london. stay with us on
the briefing. also on the programme... pick
up a penguin — we'll tell you about the
thriving colony of birds enjoying life off
the antarctic peninsula. first the place slid
gently off the restaurant tables, then suddenly
the people, the tables on the chairs crashed
sideways and downwards and it was just a matter
of seconds until the very lurched onto our
side. a hydrogen bomb on a remote pacific
atoll. the americans have successfully tested
a weapon which dwarfs the force of the bomb
dropped on hiroshima.
i had heard the news earlier and my heart
went bang and bang. the constitutional rights
of these marshals are the rights of the citizens
of the us, and they should be protected so
they do not get their heads broken and sent
to hospital. this religious controversy, i
know you don't want to say much about it,
but will it boil up when you get to the state?
it worries me, but i think i'm going to be
all right you're watching the briefing. 0ur
headlines: heavy snowfall and deadly blizzards
will continue to lash many parts of europe
into the weekend, forcing airports to cancel
or delay flights and rail services to stop
trains around the continent. our top story
— in a few hours, britain's prime minister
will set out her vision for britain's trading
relationship with the european union after
brexit. let's stay with that now.
with me is dr elaine fahey, reader in european
law at city university here in london. good
morning. thank you for coming in. this is
being billed as a real step forward and from
what we have seen step forward and from what
we have seen about what the prime minister
was going to say, do you think it is? is difficult
to have a step forward after the obligation
of the eu draft treaty on wednesday. my understanding
is that this is sound bites and the eu needs
to see the detail of what the uk in visages
going forward. one year before we have to
leave, and we are still talking about what
we want never mind actually deciding what
we want. theresa may is struggling to unite
her own party and satisfy the demands of the
eu at the same time. it is almost impossible
balancing act that she is juggling but the
uk signed up in december two seconds set up
as a pulse of the treaty published on wednesday
is not
necessarily so different. it is difficult
to see how this division in the face of uk
agreement, as of december. what do you think
we will hear about northern ireland, which
isa hear about northern ireland, which is
a sticking point, as we heard in the withdrawal
agreement published on wednesday? the eu envisages
something that the british prime minister
says will not allow to happen. how are they
going to come together on this? the treaty
is saying, this is an entity for the purposes
of law, and the uk is signed up to the integrity
of the single market and to have alignment
and a frictionless border, and there was concern
in the eu that there are still not a viable
technology from the uk about the technology,
and it is difficult to see how this is going
to move forward without some
very specific proposals in this speech today.
they think the eu is becoming increasingly
intra nsigent orders arejust seen becoming
increasingly intra nsigent orders are just
seen that way from their tough language and
you think they would be prepared to see deal?
the fact the remains that there is no precedent
for what the uk wants, and the eu has a variety
of partnerships out there, although these
are not something that the uk was to sign
up to so that puts the eu ina was to sign
up to so that puts the eu in a difficult position
as they are to satisfy the uk's needs in the
absence of detail. good to get your thoughts.
we'll focus on a speech in a couple of hours'
time. here's our briefing on some of the key
events happening later. we begin in new york
for the opening of the "david bowie is" exhibition.
then later president donald trump's former
campaign manager paul manafort will appear
in a us court to be arraigned on a second
indictment filed against him.the new 32—count
indictment alleges he committed bank fraud
and filed false tax returns. and later on
in paris, the french equivalent of the oscars
kicks off. at this year's cesars the aids
drama
120 bpm and world war i drama au revoir la—haut
are among the favourites. now it's time to
get all the latest from the bbc sports centre.
hello there, coming up in your friday sport
briefing, american deontay wilder has his
eyes on andyjoshua, despite his wbc heavyweight
title defence in new york this weekend against
luis 0rtiz. the world indoor athletics continues
and cliff diving in the azores sounds nice.
but you may want to think again when you see
what it involves. deontay wilder will defend
his wbc heavyweight title against cuban, luiz
0rtiz on saturday when they meet in new york.
the american holds one of the four heavyweight
titles and is already talking about a potential
unification fight against briton, andyjoshua.
but speaking to the bbc, obstacles are being
put up byjoshua's promoter, eddie hearn.
i don't believe they want it. and when i say
they, i mean eddie. eddie hearn, i don't believe
eddie hearn wants this fight at all. why not?
because, like i say, joshua is like annabel
the cow, eddie hearn is milking him. milking
him, every dollar. every dollar. the world
indoor aathletics championships are underway
in birmingham and there is plenty to feast
your eyes on later. the south african is the
strong favourite in the long jump final on
friday night. the showpiece event is the women's
60 metres final where all eyes will be on
elaine thomson. the double olympic champion
is hoping to get her season back on track
after some poor form. the jamaican hasn't
come close to the time she posted last year.
in case you missed it, a sparsely filled emirates
stadium in north london. arsenal were given
a first— half footballing lesson by manchester
city in the premier league just days after
being beaten by the same team in the league
cup final.
three first half goals led by german international,
leroy sane, who scored one himself, wasn't
at the interval vote. arsenal failed to score
and saw aubameyang have a penalty saved, heaping
more pressure on gunners' boss, arsene wenger.
physically, certainly, our highest game of
the season. them as well, we played with low
confidence and we could see that at the start
of the game and we paid for it. they were
a quality team and they took advantage of
that. after that, we maintained and we needed
the penalty to go in to have a little chance
to come back. that was another negative in
the second half. in the end, we lost against
a team which is the best in the country at
the moment. the spanish leaders, barcelona
extended their club record unbeaten league
run to 33 games, but they could only manage
a 1—1 draw to las palmas. lionel messi gave
barcelona the lead just after the 20 minute
mark,
but a second—half penalty rescued it for
the canary islands hosts. the catalans moved
five points clear of atletico madrid, when
it comes to cliff diving, you need lots of
skill and dedication, but above all, you need
guts. just take a look at this. this cliff
diver posted this of himself in the azores
in the atlantic. the american says i am scared
of the potential consequences of a cliff dive
gone wrong. almost as much as having to hold
and nine to five office job. i know how he
feels. you can get all those stories on our
website. from me, that is your friday sport
briefing. an international team including
scientists from oxford university has discovered
a thriving colony
of more than 750,000 penguins off the antarctic
peninsula. with little human activity on the
danger islands, a so—called super—colony
of adelie penguins is thriving. whilst the
same species is in decline on the other side
of the peninsula. 0ur science correspondent
victoria gill has more. a bird's eye view
of a super colony. three quarters of a million
adelie penguins are nesting here on the a
ptly penguins are nesting here on the aptly
named danger islands just east of the antarctic
peninsula. it
was only when a team of british and us scientists
mounted an expedition to the wrote, rocky
islands that they we re the wrote, rocky islands
that they were able to carry out a detailed
penguin centres. painstaking headcounts with
aerial photography revealed the scale of this
wildlife haven. ijoined the team of researchers
in antarctica in 2016 and captured a snapshot
of their
decade of wildlife monitoring in this frozen
landscape. worked like this frozen landscape.
worked like this on the ground in the antarctic
has revealed that adelie penguins in the rest
of the peninsular are in decline service discoveryjust
100 decline service discoveryjust100 miles
away provides a vital clue about a site that
can be a refuge for the birds. and it might
need more protection from human activities
like fishing. 0ne more protection from human
activities like fishing. one key to this island's
fast stable colony is the sea ice. as well
as being a vital breeding ground for the crusta
cea ns vital breeding ground for the crustaceans
and cruel that penguins rely on it makes access
to the island is difficult for fishing and
shipping. is a proposalto island is difficult
for fishing and shipping. is a proposal to
make the sea shipping. is a proposal to make
the sea around the danger islands marine protected
area. scenes like this show just what that
could preserve. great to see them thriving
there. sticking with the cold theme — denmark
may be in the depths of a freezing and rather
dark winter but its capital copenhagen is
awash with light.
it's for the city's first international light
festival. a total of a0 illuminated artworks
dot the quay, small parks and buildings, with
danish elements of minimalism, sustainability
and scandinavian design featuring heavily.
0rganisers say the festival is aimed at getting
the danes out of the house in winter, to see
copenhagen in a new light. that's pretty spectacular.
stay with me on bbc news, i'll be back with
the business briefing in just a few moments
— we'll have more on president trump's move
to slap tariffs on imported steel — plus
the economic challenges facing italy. tell
me what you think about our talking point
today — with transport chaose all over europe
and people stuck in their cars for hours — we're
asking if we've all been woefully underprepared
for the beast from the east — even though
we knew it was coming. i have been very disappointed
with
the gritting, or the lack of it, in my area.
stay with us here on bbc news so much more
to come. we've seen treacherous conditions
in the uk and there are more warnings from
the met office, with amber weather warning
still in force across scotland, northern ireland
and the north east of england with frequent
showers, those warnings expiring at 10am.
by the early hours of the morning we will
have lost that red warning towards the south—west
and wales, but there are still that amber
weather warning until eight o'clock or so.
that's no we have been seeing has been particularly
bad in hampshire, and that has been due to
a combination of storm emma and the cold air
brought about by the beast from the east.
dennis taylor: as low as they have been, but
there are still the strong wind around and
a good deal of cloud. those snow showers continue
across the north and east of scotla nd across
the north and east of scotland running through
the central belt and the north east of england.
and we could see more snow developing not
just and we could see more snow developing
notjust across northern
ireland and wales but in southern england,
especially during the afternoon, and patch
is slowly work its way north, with some uncertainty
about how much snow we will get during the
day on friday. another called david temperatures
struggling to get above freezing, and we still
have that easterly winds that is what it's
going to feel like if you're out in the wind.
another very cold day ahead. things are going
to change. the beast from the east, that strong
easterly wind being replaced by something
a little less cold, coming up from the south,
with the weather beginning to come from southern
climes rather than all the way from siberia,
so we should see temperatures lifting, slowly.
we still have the threat of more snow showers
across northern parts of the uk will restore
still have a cold, easterly wind. further
south, the winds will becoming lighter and
it should be driver soweto weather beginning
to arrive in the south later but by the most
part, this should be rain. over the hills,
we could see some snow pushing northwards
overnight towards the borders and across northern
england,
with some wetter weather returning to southern
areas. a messy purge on sunday, losing that
cold, easterly wind, the winds should be lighter
and temperatures will be rising to around
eight or nine in the south, across the northern
isles, temperatures will not be as low. gradually
becoming less cold across southern parts,
but they're still a risk of some rain, but
also, some snow.