this is the briefing.
i'm sally bundock.
our top stories: president trump says he wants
to ban bump-stock devices that turn rifles
into rapid-fire weapons.
is that enough for survivors of the florida
school shooting?
controlling the nile - at a cost.
concerns that africa's biggest hydroelectric
dam could provoke a regional conflict.
no thaw in relations between the us and north
korea.
washington says pyongyang pulled out of high
level talks in seoul at the last minute.
and a front row seat at london fashion week.
the queen makes a surprise appearance.
in business briefing, south korea signs trade
deals with central american countries - but
can they offer a back door into the us as
tensions grow between the two?
plus the pressure intensifies
on prime minister may as she faces a fresh
outcry from more than sixty mp’s in her
party demanding a hard brexit - we'll have
the latest.
a warm welcome to the programme, briefing
you on all you need to know in global news,
business, and sport. and you can be part of
the conversation.
after the queen stole the show at london fashion
week and presented her new award for emerging
british designers, we're asking you - how
would you encourage young talent?
do tell us what you think.
just use the hashtag #bbcthebriefing.
so let's it started.
-- get.
apparently in response to a growing gun control
campaign by high school students, president
trump has expressed his willingness to ban
the so-called "bump stock" mechanism, which
turns a rifle into something very close to
a machine gun.
bump stocks allow a rifle to shoot in almost
automatic bursts, and were used by the gunman
who shot dead 58 people in las vegas in october.
laura westbrook reports.
they are mobilised and organised, and they
are demanding lawmakers in their state of
florida take action on gun control.
3000 kids in one school?
that's a big family enough.
and having a lot of the nation coming and
supporting us, too, that's what is changing.
like we're able to have that voice,
and we're able to be heard.
the president says he is listening.
i signed a memorandum directing the attorney
general to propose regulations to ban all
devices that turn legal weapons into machine-guns.
i expect that these critical regulations will
be finalised very soon.
so-called "bump stocks" allow semiautomatic
guns to be modified to fire hundreds of rounds
every minute.
the devices were used by the man who killed
58 people in las vegas last september.
-- 0ctober.
chanting: enough is enough! it's a sign that
the president is feeling the pressure from
these young voices.
here he is, a year ago, at a rally hosted
by the national rifle association.
they gave millions of dollars towards the
trump campaign.
so let me make a simple promise to every one
of the freedom-loving americans in the audience
today.
as your president, i will never, ever infringe
on the right of people to keep and bear arms.
never ever.
it remains to be seen if congress will push
through any new legislation.
so far, the nra have successfully resisted
every move to tighten gun controls.
but the children who are targets of school
shootings are hoping they can make it harderfor
this kind of tragedy to happen again.
another funeral was held for 15-year-old peter
wang. he was killed while trying to help others
escape, and honoured by being posthumously
accepted into his dream school, the westpoint
academy.
laura westbrook, bbc news.
many of you have already messaged
and said that you do not think that is enough.
the united nations in syria says it's deeply
worried for hundreds of thousands of people
trapped under a mounting government bombardment
of the rebel-held enclave of eastern ghouta.
the un said it feared a second aleppo, the
syrian city recaptured in a government offensive
in 2016.
activists said at least 250 people had been
killed in eastern ghouta since sunday night,
the highest 48-hour total in the syrian conflict
since 2013.
the drones target the areas here, and target
the civilians, and the crowded neighbourhood.
they want to
kill iran here.
-- everyone.
the project to build africa's biggest hydroelectric
dam on the river nile is threatening to provoke
a major conflict between some of the countries
affected.
the dam is being build by ethiopia and sudan
says it welcomes the prospect of cheaper power
and the ability to reduce flooding in its
vast irrigation projects.
but the egyptians are deeply unhappy fearing
the flow through the aswan dam and on to cairo
will be weakened in a country already facing
serious water shortages.
0ur africa correspondent alastair leithead
has travelled to all three countries and he
sent this special report.
the river nile is the world's lammas river.
but these are turbulent times between three
countries that share it's like bringing water.
the source
is this.
five years in and to those built, this multi-
billion-dollar dam can already control the
flow of the nile, and that is what is upsetting
downstream egypt. when it is finished, this
will be the largest hydroelectric power station
in africa. in one of the biggest dams on the
continent.
it will not just power this country but the
surrounding countries as well.
if you have it did not even asked the country
‘s downstream before it started building.
that is the scale of this country's ambition.
the reservoir at rates will be bigger than
greater london.
hydroelectric dams do not consume water, but
if it is still too quickly, the flow of the
nile, 85% of which comes from here, will be
reduced.
ethiopian’s obsessed with electrification.
70% of people here do not have power.
it is betting on economic growth and
industrial revolution, often at the cost of
human rights and freedom of speech, to destroy
its image of drought and speech, to destroy
its image of droughtand famine.
speech, to destroy its image of drought and
famine. it is an important project for ethiopia.
it is not about control and the flow, it is
really about an opportunity for us to develop
ourselves.
the powerlines are ready and waiting to ta
ke powerlines are ready and waiting to take
cheap sustainable energy.
at the great confluence of the blue-and-white
nile in khartoum, there are huge agricultural
projects under way.
much of this cattle feed is destined for the
goal.
the new dam would stop flooding and regulate
the river's flow.
it is the best thing that has happened for
a long
time.
regular water levels is a great blessing.
sudan has had a decades long deal with egypt.
but now it is in a conflict over how much
water it can use.
regional rivalries here go back to the pyramids.
egypt was once ruled from here thousands of
years ago.
hours on the nile rise and fall.
luxor’s temples represent thousands of years
of egypt's powers set in temples represent
thousands of years of egypt’s powers set
in stone, temples represent thousands of years
of egypt's powers set in stone, a proud symbol
of the nation's identity.
this man has been a fisherman on the nile
for years.
he is concerned.
translation: they said the
water will not be affected, but only god knows
what will happen.
if they jammed the river, there will be wars
and fighting.
but it is not a fee to be taken and fighting.
but it is not a fee to be ta ken lightly.
and fighting.
but it is not a fee to be taken lightly.
egypt relies on the nile for most of its water.
-- it is not a feud to be taken lightly.
ethiopia's dam makes them angry.
what does it mean? lost 200,000 acres of land.
one acre at least makes one family survive.
an average family size in egypt is about five
persons.
thei million would be jobless.
the impact of the dam has not been properly
assessed. in the battle between the power
of egypt and the emerging ambitions of ethiopia.
wars over water can be avoided with strong
leadership and diplomacy.
but now it is down to ethiopia, sudan, and
egypt, to navigate tensions on the world's
long as river.
-- longest.
let's brief you on some of the other stories
making the news.
american officials say the north korean leader's
sister was due to meet the us vice-president
for secret talks during the winter olympics,
but pulled out, less than two hours beforehand.
mike pence was apparently due to meet a delegation
from pyongyang but his officials claim it
was called off after he condemned human rights
abuses in the north.
we'll be speaking to our correspondent in
seoul later in the programme.
a lawyer from new york, who's the son-in-law
of one of russia's richest men, has admitted
lying to fbi agents investigating russian
attempts to interfere in the 2016 us presidential
election.
alex van der zwaan pleaded guilty to misleading
the fbi about his contacts with a former trump
campaign aide.
he'll be sentenced in april.
now here in the uk, hardline brexiteers, led
by conservative mp jacob rees-mogg, are threatening
to withdraw there support for theresa may's
brexit plans
if they think they'll keep britain too closely
aligned to the eu. with me is henry bonsu
who's a broadcaster and international conference
host.
good to see you.
nash is under renewed pressure.
absolutely.
the title suggests a link, but it is anything
but.
there will be discussing exactly the nature
of the deal that the government is trying
to deal with the european union.
and whether or not they will be to change
the alignment. and the brexiteers, who number
of 60, about a fifth of the tory party, they
want
any limitation period to be based on wto principles.
that suggest they wa nt wto principles.
that suggest they want a hard brexit and everything
that goes with it.
in the meantime, it is critical to her that
she gets cabinet on board.
borisjohnson is a key player, foreign secretary.
david davis has been talking to business leaders
in various other places, and theresa may,
they are trained to get their message out
there.
the one yesterday by david davis indiana presented
a picture of a britain that was in lockstep
with the european union, not sliding towards
a dystopian mad max style future, he was trained
to reassure people that we we re was trained
to reassure people that we were not going
to take cliff edge, but this letter is in
stark contracts that.
henry will be back.
his cadaver coffee and he has other stories
get his head around.
we will talk you through those.
-- he is
going for a coffee.
and we look forward to the competition in
zhenjiang -- pyeongchang.
nine years and 15,000 deaths after going in
to afghanistan, the last soviet troops were
finally coming home.
the withdrawal completed in good order, but
the army defeated in the task it had been
sent to perform.
malcolm was murdered.
that has a terrible effect on the morale of
the people.
i'm terrified of the repercussions in the
streets.
one wonders who is next.
as the airlift got underway, there was no
let-up in the eruption itself.
lava streams from a vent low in the crater
flow down to the sea on the east of the island,
away from the town
for the time being, but it could start flowing
again at any time.
the russians heralded their new generation
space station with a spectacular night launch.
they've called it mir, the russian for peace.
you're watching the briefing.
our headlines: survivors of the florida school
shooting have arrived in the state capital
to push for gun control.
president trump says he wants to ban ‘bump-stock’
devices that turn rifles into rapid-fire weapons.
washington says north korea pulled out of
high level talks with the us at the last minute,
stifling hopes for a thaw in relations.
let's stay with that now.
let's speak to the bbc’s stephen mcdonell
who's in the south korean capital, seoul.
we heard, we remember well the
speech of mike pence just before the winter
olympics started.
in some ways, it is not surprising to hear
that north korea was not happy with what he
had to say and will out of talk.
-- pulled out of talks.
what he had to say and will out of talk.
this story of mike pence and the sister of
kimjong-un, kim yo-jong. it gets more fascinating,
there were secret effo rts more fascinating,
there were secret efforts behind the scenes
for them to meet and the north koreans pulled
out at the last minute.
i think washington has released details because
it is trying to counter the criticism that
mike pence came here and didn't reach out
to the north koreans, that this was a wasted
opportunity and he could have spoken to them.
if the white house version of events is correct,
it means he was sitting there in the main
stadium at the opening ceremony in front of
the north korean leader's sister, within handshakes
distance
and didn't even say something like see you
tomorrow.
at that point he still thought the meeting
was on.
it turns out the next day they were going
to meet at the blue house, a delegation from
the north korean side and the us side, but
at the dying moments, within hours before
the meeting was supposed to take place, the
north koreans pulled out.
this is on the same day that the invitation
came from kim jong-un via his sisterfor invitation
came from kim jong-un via his sister for south
korea's president to visit the north.
there area president to visit the north.
there are a lot of chess pieces being moved
around the board at this stage.
they are both reaching for the propaganda
high ground.
what this does show, i guess, that the attempt
by south korea's president to pull both sides
together, fabled. he apparently is the one
who has been the intermediary, suggesting
to mike pence that he meet with the north
korean. he will be
disappointed that that meeting didn't take
place.
i am sure there will be frustrating that that
didn't ta ke will be frustrating that that
didn't take place.
very delicate.
we will keep you up-to-date as we hear more.
slovakia angered the eu when it joined poland,
hungary and the czech republic in refusing
to accept migrant quotas.
these countries became known as the eu's trouble
makers, but slovakia actually favours closer
eu integration.
in the last of her series from the east of
the eu, jenny hill reports from slovakia.
this country is going places.
slovakia's and eu success story, foreign investment,
a soaring economy, the euros are pouring in.
no wonder perhaps, when brussels speaks, rattus
lover is all he is.
now is a big version of what has
happened with angela merkel, together with
emmanuel macron, put on the table this reform.
the communists are long gone, but it's socialist
past still casts a shadow.
translation: some things we did back then
and it would be good if they continued.
-- were good.
education and the health system work, but
we started to change everything to the western
way. in this region, slovakia often stands
alone, a flag bearerfor slovakia often stands
alone, a flag bearer for brussels and that
this was several reasons but perhaps the most
striking is this.
unlike its neighbours, poland, hungary, slovakia
doesn't have a strong nationalist voice.
rarely do slovaks feel that their country's
interest and those of the eu's are at odds.
u nless and those of the eu's are at odds.
unless you are talking about migrant quotas.
robert fico and his allies
oppose them.
translation: this union of prime ministers,
he says, doesn't wa nt of prime ministers,
he says, doesn't want was in communities created
in their countries.
but unlike poland, hungary and the czech republic,
that is where the anti-eu rhetoric stops.
in their logic, they are bringing slovakia
to the heart of europe as it means economic
benefits for the country and these are important
for providing jobs, but also protecting people.
unfortunately sometimes protecting means protecting
migrants orforeigners.
protecting means protecting migrants or foreigners.
and forging a different future.
new customers, it new investors.
-- new investors.
in the south, old injury -- industry left
behind, car manufacturers, among them, france
and germany pay
slovakia's bills now.
translation: living standards are not the
same as those in other member states.
in germany they earned four more times as
we do.
if we are talking about the european union,
it should equal.
life in the eu was supposed to look like this.
handouts for slovakia's roma, the wealth doesn't
flow this far.
translation: if anyone told me ten yea rs
far.
translation: if anyone told me ten years ago
that something like existed here in the 21st
century, i wouldn't have believed them.
people don't have drinking water, hot water
or even running water.
but here, on the margins of the eu, a country
dreams of getting to its heart.
jenny l, bbc news, practice lover.
-- bratislava.
here's our briefing on some of the key events
happening later.
we begin in paris where french
interior minister gerard collomb unveils a
controversial new bill on migrants and asylum
seekers.
it's believed he will push the uk to accept
more refugees and unaccompanied minors.
later in florida, students from marjory stoneman
douglas will march in the state capital of
tallahassee in the first organised protest
of their #neveragain movement.
17 people were left dead in a shooting at
the school last week.
and in london, the world's top musical talent
celebrate the 2018 brit awards.
dua lipa leads the pack with five nominations.
let's get the latest on the winter olympics
in pyongchang.
italy's sofia goggia won italy's first gold
with a win in the women's downhill.
norway's ragnhild mowinckel took silver and
the american - lindsey vonn - a former champion,
was pushed into 3rd place for bronze. in the
ladies figure skating, russia's15-year-old
alina zagitova is the favourite.
the european champion faces strong competition
in the short programme from her team mate
evgenia medvedeva and canada's gabrielle daleman.
in curling, the final rounds for a place in
the semi finals are underway.
team gb women outplayed the reigning world
and olympic champions canada, but their victory
was only assured in the very final game.
the hosts korea are already through.
the men from team gb face the usa. the queen
has attended london fashion week for the first
time in her 66 year reign. she sat in the
front row of a show by an up-and-coming designer
richard quinn, next to the woman often hailed
as the queen of fashion, vogue magazine's
anna wintour.
virginia langeberg reports.
it was the queen's first visit to london fashion
week and, of course, her majesty made a show-stopping
entrance, bringing the audience to their feet.
after a few introductory words with the vip
guests, it was time to settle in.
those beside the monarch
were conscious to follow royal protocol before
taking their seats.
then it was showtime.
big and bold designs lit up the runway.
no crowds on this catwalk, but at least some
helmets to help hide any potential nerves.
never before has london fashion week's famous
power front row seen fashion royalty sit alongside
the queen herself.
her majesty, wearing a light blue tweed dress
and jacket, next to vogue's editor-in-chief,
dame anna wintour.
the pair sharing a laugh and keeping a close,
discerning eye on the show.
ms wintour opted to keep her sunglasses on,
but the queen's delight was captured in several
snaps and quickly beamed around the world,
causing the internet to heat up like never
before.
it was the last day of fashion week and they
were watching the work of emerging designer
richard quinn. he received the very first
queen elizabeth ii award
for british design.
even he didn't believe the guest list when
he saw it.
it was really surreal.
before the show, you saw the names on this
blue cushion, and you're like, "oh, it's not
a prank, it's actually real!" the queen's
style was given a nod by the chief executive
of the british fashion council, who described
the 91-year-old monarch as a fashion icon.
speaking after the runway show, the queen
said her award for emerging designers will
be her legacy to british fashion.
virginia langeberg, bbc news.
we asked you, what would you try to do to
encourage young talent? we have got stephen
lang caster, he said given a big say.
i would encourage them, not put them down.
a man in india says good moments like these
do happen.
the queen represents tradition and standard,
fashion is a trending lifestyle.
i
will see you in a moment.
thanks forjoining me.
time we updated you on the weather prospects
for the whole of the british isles over the
next few days or so.
fairly slow change, i would've thought, over
the next few days, simply because we are developing
an area of high pressure, which has rather
strangled the life out of the old weather
front, which provided quite a veil of cloud
sometimes through eastern parts of the british
isles through tuesday, but with the development
of the high pressure close by to the british
isles, that, as i say, has the effect of killing
off that front.
a veil of cloud, not much more than that.
maybe the odd drib and drab of rain, but essentially,
it's a dry pattern, and, increasingly, we'll
be talking about high pressure linked to the
one over scandinavia as we go through the
weekend and indeed into next week.
the veil of cloud doing its stuff to keep
temperatures above freezing across england
and wales for the most part.
scotland and northern ireland, a different
kettle of fish, someone's going to get to
“11 or -5.
so here we are on the new day.
a little bit of mist and fog around,
particularly in scotland and northern ireland,
but that will soon pop away.
essentially, it's a dry day.
maybe the odd spot of rain passing by, maybe
a shower coming in on the north-easterly breeze
towards kent and essex.
those temperatures, not too bad when you compare
them to what's to come, and i'll show you
those in just a second.
here is thursday.
just the first signs of us wanting to pick
up something a little bit sort of continental
in origin.
certainly, that wind coming in from a pretty
cool continent at the moment, and you'll feel
the like of that in norwich, for example,
4 degrees only, and generally across the british
isles, despite the fact there's a lot of sunshine
around, variable amounts of cloud, temperatures
just beginning to tick away from where we
were at the start of the week.
so as we move towards the tail end of the
week, things beginning to settle down.
notice temperatures around the 5, 6, 7-degree
mark or so.
the forecast in edinburgh rather caught my
eye.
that's the second big fixture of saturday
when we get round to the next round of the
six nations rugby.
i don't think the weather
will get in the way in dublin or, indeed,
in edinburgh. as i say, once we get towards
the weekend, our high pressure begins to become
amalgamated with a big area of high pressure
over scandinavia.
now, that's really quite important, because,
if you follow the isobars around the eastern
and southern flanks, then we begin to look
away, up towards siberia, for the source of
the air that comes towards us as we start
the new week, and that's really quite crucial.
we haven't seen that sort of setup for quite
a while, but there's no doubt about it.
next week, yes, there will be some sunshine,
there will be some chilly nights around.
a bitter wind in from the east and the chance
of snow as temperatures tumble.