this is bbc news. our top stories: a new trade
threat from donald trump. tariffs on european
cars if the eu retaliates over steel. syrian
government forces advance into the besieged
enclave of ghouta. 100 people are reported
killed in the past week. video assisted referees
are cleared for international football. they
could be used in this summer's world cup.
and will theyjoin germany's next government?
social democrats add up the votes. president
trump has stepped up his war of words on trade
tariffs, suggesting he would "apply a tax"
on imports of cars from the european union.
it comes two days after he promised hefty
tariffs on steel and aluminium imports.
in a tweet, he said other countries had taken
advantage of the us for years. andrew plant
reports. the white hot glow of steel. this
multibillion-dollar global industry has sparked
heated threats of trade tariffs and friction
between the us and europe. it's disgraceful.
and when it comes to a time when our country...
on thursday, donald trump announced plans
to levy a 25% tax on steel imports and 10%
on aluminium. the current deals, he said,
bad for the usa economy. european commission
president jean-claude juncker said the eu
could retaliate in kind with tariffs of its
own on things the us sells to europe. we buy
more steel from the united states than any
other country... canada, too, opposed the
idea, justin trudeau urging mr trump to reconsider.
..would be significant and serious.
now donald trump has hit back, threatening
to increase tax on imported european cars.
america, the eu's biggest car market. in a
tweet, he said: as yet, there's been no retaliatory
response, the press secretary simply saying
that no-one should be surprised at mr trump's
announcements. mr trump says other countries
have taken advantage of the us for years because
of what he called "very stupid" trade deals.
it's the latest salvo in a war of words over
trade tariffs - as our north america correspondent,
chris buckler, explains. yes, the threat of
new tariffs has fuelled fears of a trade war
but you are right in saying that the war of
words is well under way.
countries had already threatened retaliatory
action as a result of president trump's announcement
that he was preparing to put 25% tariffs on
steel and and 10% on aluminium being imported
into america. and probably one of the most
memorable warnings came from the european
commission presidentjean-claude juncker, who
said that they would tax the most american
of products, including bourbon and bluejeans.
while it is clear that president trump was
listening and today he bit back, it probably
will not come as a surprise to anyone that
he responded on twitter, saying that he was
prepared to tax cars coming into the us from
europe and it will cause concern across the
atlantic because the european car manufacturers’
biggest export market is the us. however,
there are many inside the white house who
are urging caution because they believe that
no-one really benefits from this kind of tit-for-tat
trade war. syrian government forces have gained
more ground in their assault on the last major
rebel-held enclave near damascus. one monitoring
group says they now control 10% of eastern
ghouta.
disturbing footage has emerged, showing aid
workers carrying an injured man into a van,
being targeted in an air-strike, but then
managing to escape. from neighbouring lebanon,
yolande knell reports. after days of air strikes
and shelling, fighting on the ground in eastern
ghouta has recently intensified, and the uk-based
monitoring group the syrian observatory for
human rights says that government forces have
now recaptured two areas of the east and south-east
of the besieged enclave, where an estimated
400,000 people are trapped. rebels, in turn,
shelled damascus. more than 100 civilians
are reported to have been killed in eastern
ghouta since the united nations security council
called for a ceasefire one week ago. shouting.
on
another front in the many-sided
syrian war, turkey says it has captured a
kurdish town in the northern region of afrin.
at least 36 pro-syrian government troops sent
to support kurdish forces are reported to
have been killed by a turkish air strike.
six weeks ago, turkey launched a military
offensive in the area to clear it of kurdish
militia, which it sees as terrorists. our
middle east correspondent yolande knell reporting.
let's take a look at some of the other stories
making the news. an extremist group affiliated
to al-qaeda in mali says it carried out the
two deadly bombings on friday in burkina faso’s
capital, ouagadougou. eight members of the
security forces were killed and more than
80 people were wounded in the attacks on the
army headquarters and french embassy.
the prime minister paul kaba thieba has visited
the scene and described it as "post-apocalyptic".
the funeral has taken place in slovakia of
the murdered investigative journalist, jan
kuciak. hundreds of mourners attended the
ceremony in the village of stiavnik, a day
after the burial of his fiancee, who was shot
dead at the same time. mr kuciak’s last
article focused on alleged ties between the
italian mafia and government officials. the
us secret service says a man has shot and
killed himself outside the white house in
washington. no-one else was injured in the
incident, which triggered a big security alert.
president trump was at his estate in florida
when the shooting happened. in one of the
biggest shake-ups in football for years, it
appears the world cup in russia will use video
technology, to assist referees. the system,
known as var, lets referees review controversial
incidents such as disputed goals or penalties.
the body which sets the rules for world football
has voted
to approve it after a series of top-level
trials, even though some of the decisions
have proved controversial. here's our sports
news reporter richard conway. from diego maradona's
hand of god to injustice in the biggest games.
football has long opposed technology to help
officials make the important decisions. but
after an historic vote all that has changed.
video assisted referees or var as it's known,
finally given the go-ahead. var is good for
football. it's good for refereeing. it brings
more fairness in the game. and, for these
reasons, we have decided to approve. var will
be used to correct errors relating to goals,
penalties, straight red cards and mistaken
identity. nearly 1000 games have formed part
of the two year var experiment. tottenham's
match against rochdale last week was included
in the trial
but was criticised given lengthy delays while
the referee reviewed incidents, leading to
claims technology is killing the atmosphere
and pace of the match. but one of the architects
of the new system told me there's evidence
that video assistance is working. on sort
of clear error situations, clear situations,
the accuracy of the referee's decisions went
from initially 93% up to around 99%. of course
there are grey areas where an incident could
be a penalty, could not be a penalty, and
they will always remain grey areas. var will
almost certainly now be used at this summer's
world cup. however, several premier league
clubs are said to be more cautious and may
opt to delay its implementation with football's
lawmakers admitting there's still work to
be done. i think the communication with the
crowd, the speeding up of reviews, the flow
of the game, the spectator-spectacle, i think
has all got to be worked on, but we've also
got to have the confidence to sell it to people.
it is a change but it's actually a small change
to make a big difference. football's leaders
want to eliminate game-changing mistakes,
but as the experiments have shown, anyone
who thinks technology will stop controversy
may want to think again. richard conway, bbc
news. dr kristen wells is a sports psychologist
who's worked with women professional golfers
and in minor league baseball. i asked her
how she thinks var technology in football
will change the game. well, it depends on
the player and it depends on, in whose favour
the call goes toward. so the team that the
call is in favour of will certainly always
be happy. the team that the call goes against
will not be so happy. the issue is the momentum.
and, you know, if a team is in the zone and
suddenly, we are going to go to instant replay
- or var, as it is called - then you lose
that momentum. but, again, if the call goes
in favour of the team, the momentum lost isn't
going to be such a big deal.
for the other team, however, it could actually
then be an even further detriment to them.
but in terms of momentum, if you take, say,
rugby union- i don't know whether you know
how it works, being american - forgive me
- but with rugby union, they're used to having
a video assistant referee and it is just part
of the game, theyjust get on with it. right.
well, and here in the states, if you look
at american football, it is not such a big
deal because it has been around for so - it's
been around for decades. major league baseball
had just implemented it and so, you know,
they have been fortunate, they got to learn
from american football. and so, it - the implementation
of it wasn't - hasn't been so bad, or at least
from the perspective of players and officials
and all,
it has not been a bad thing at all. it takes
time. fans will have to get used to it, players
will have to get used to it, and certainly,
officials will get used to it, but overall,
it is probably a good thing. what does this
do for the way that the game is perceived
because people say that basically, if you
get rid of human error, then there will be
nothing to talk about. but i'm not so sure
fans who are on the losing side agree with
that! i think there's always going to be human
error and, you know, it is... do you lose
a little bit of the human aspect to it? probably
so. is that a good thing? probably not. from
a psychological perspective, you know, i personally
would say i would hate to see you lose the
human piece of it. but if you look at the
benefits of using it, so say, for example,
officials - we know research was done and
what they found was that with video replay,
they went from 93% accuracy up to 98%, almost
99%, and how can you complain about that?
i mean, 93% is brilliant.
i mean - but the thing is, if you ask a football
fan that would probably say that referees
were always getting the calls wrong, not realising
that actually, they are doing a good job.
the funeral has taken place of the murdered
slovakian journalist, jan kuciak. his fiancee
martina kusnirova, who was also shot dead,
was buried on friday. he'd been investigating
alleged ties between the italian mafia and
slovak government officials. it's heightened
tensions within slovakia's coalition government,
with interior minister robert kalinak refusing
to resign over the issue. russell trott reports.
in the eastern border, jan kuciak elite hundreds
of mourners who had arrived from across slovakia
for his burial. just 27 he was shot dead last
week,
along with his fiancee, martina kusnirova,
he was buried a day earlier. her parents were
also in attendance. there were two months
away from their wedding day. she'd been buried
in her wedding dress. the murders have shocked
this small central european country. there
have been protests in 25 cities, with many
venting their frustration at the prime minister
and his government, accusing it with links
to organised crime. he has denied any wrongdoing.
jan kuciak’s last article focused on alleged
ties between the italian mafia and officials.
seven people questioned by police have since
been released. the government has offered
a reward ofi million euros to find those responsible.
he has vowed his government would protect
freedom of speech and the safety of journalists.
this is the first killing of a journalist
in
slovakia's street. jan kuciak’s collea g
u es slovakia's street. jan kuciak’s colleagues
fear it may not be the last. stay with us
on bbc news, still to come: could the techniques
of ancient mayans save guatemala from the
curse of plastic? weavers work to end the
country's waste problem. first, the plates
slipped gently off the restaurant tables,
then suddenly the tables, the chairs and people
crashed sideways and downwards, and it was
just a matter of seconds as the ferry lurched
on to her side. the hydrogen bomb. on a remote
pacific atoll, the americans have successfully
tested a weapon whose explosive force dwarfed
that of the bomb dropped on hiroshima. i heard
the news earlier and so my heart went bang,
bang! the constitutional rights of these marchers
are their rights as citizens of the united
states, and they should be protected, even
in the right to test them out, so they don't
get their heads broken
and are sent to hospital. this religious controversy,
i know you don't want to say too much about
it, but does it worry you that it's going
to boil up when you get to the states? well,
it worries me, yes, but i hope everything
will be all right in the end, as they say.
this is bbc news. the latest headlines: president
trump has threatened to impose more tariffs
on imported goods. he's tweeted that if the
eu increases barriers for american companies,
then the us will apply a tax on eu cars. a
british-based monitoring group says pro-government
forces in syria have recaptured about 10%
of the rebel-held enclave of eastern ghouta
outside damascus. votes are being counted
in germany after a poll of members of the
social democrats on whether the party should
join a grand coalition. officials say participation
has been very high.
chancellor angela merkel’s christian democrat
union has already voted in favour. if the
social democrats also approve, it will end
the five months of political deadlock which
have followed september's vote. the result
will be announced in a few hours time, as
the bbc’s tim allman reports. never in the
history of german politics has so much attention
been devoted to the contents of one rather
unremarkable lorry. on board, hundreds of
thousands of ballot papers that, one way or
another, will decide the immediate future
of the nation. keeping an eye on proceedings,
the social democrats' acting chairman olaf
scholz and the party's leader in the bundestag,
andrea nahles, both nervously awaiting the
verdict of their membership. translation:
we already know there was a high level of
participation, so we hope we can lay a good
foundation for the renewal of the spd and,
at the same time, assess the implications
of
the result once we have it. angela merkel’s
party has already voted to renew the grand
coalition, hoping to end nearly five months
of deadlock. translation: it's up to us to
have the will to shape our country. it's up
to us to make these difficult times a success.
and it is up to us to find answers for our
party. i hope we can succeed together and
i'm optimistic, because i think we can do
it despite the difficulties. but what happens
if the social democrats say no? well, there
may be more talks to form a different type
of coalition or perhaps a minority government,
but the most likely scenario would be another
election with no guarantee of a more decisive
result. and for angela merkel and the country
she leads, there is a lot riding on this vote.
tim allman, bbc news. another country that
may soon have to confront weeks of coalition
talks is italy. the polls open there in just
under an hour's time as people vote for a
new government. immigration and high youth
unemployment have been the dominant issues
of the campaign. polls suggest the former
prime minister silvio berlusconi's centre-right
alliance could emerge as the largest bloc
in a hung parliament. julia ebner is a research
fellow at the london based institute for strategic
dialogue, who's been monitoring far-right
activity in the run-up to the election. we
have seen italian extreme right groups mobilising
across the country but also joining up and
collaborating with international far right
groups to influence the election outcome in
favour of far right parties, particular lega
nord. they have especially mobilised in the
online space, the online discourse, co-ordinating
their activity in private messaging groups
to then push it out into the mainstream. that
is something we have seen in
previous elections, especially folly the german
election campaigns that will let wi-fi the
german election campaigns that will let wi-fi
right extremist in germany and i have a tremendous
impact on setting the agenda for the online
discourse but then also influencing some of
the political topics that were actually pick
up both by the media but also then in the
debates between politicians to thatis the
debates between politicians to that is something
where we see them increasingly being able
to shape the discourse in the run-up to elections
and actually start getting into the top trends
on social media by tricking the example the
algorithms. some breaking news to bring you
now. south korea is sending a high-level delegation
to visit north korea on monday for talks that
are widely expected to focus on resuming dialogue
between the communist state and the united
states. according to state media, the south
korean president moon jae-in has named his
top security adviser and the chief of the
country's spy
agency as his special envoys to pyongyang.
the delegation is then expected to travel
to the united states. in guatemala, various
local initiatives are under way to reduce
plastic pollution in the country. a study
has reported that guatemalans use one billion
plastic bags per month. virginia langeberg
has the story. francisco is doing what he
can to try to turn around guatemala's plastic
pollution problem. using mayan fabric to make
reusable cotton bags and weave a new way forward
for local communities. it's lengthy work,
all done by hand. but for francisco, and for
the bigger picture, the payoff is worth it.
translation: when we work the land, we find
plastic bags covering the seeds, and the seeds
do not grow. it's a disaster. it is difficult
to quantify
the scale of the problem but one local university
study reported that guatemalans were using
i billion plastic bags monthly. translation:
we are being very moderate with our number,
but we know it's a problem that affects us
all. it's the equivalent of filling our local
lake five times over with the number of plastic
bags used each month. some guatemalan communities
have now ended the use of plastic bags. and
in the markets, the conscious changes can
be seen, with locals using banana leaves to
wrap food, and others replacing plastic cups
with cardboard. each change helping to tailor
a new future with less pollution. a night
of rainbow flags, sequins and flamboyant displays
has
helped celebrate a milestone year for sydney's
gay and lesbian mardi gras. hundreds of thousands
of people turned out for the massive street
party, which this year marked a0 years since
activists first marched in the city for lgbt
rights. it's also australia's first parade
since legalising same sex marriage by public
survey in december. the as warmup to its famous
gay and lesbian mardi gras parade. the 40th
anniversary of the original march and the
first since australia said yes to same-sex
marriage. and the first since australia said
yes to same-sex marriagelj and the first since
australia said yes to same-sex marriage. i
feel like this is a really important platform
for me to show myself as a middle eastern
australian in address and show a different
side of us. people that don't have my phone
number. it means being loved and acce pt number.
it means being loved and accept that and,
you know, being acknowledged. 40 years, it
is a big thing, a milestone. writing up front,
the self-styled bikes on bikes kicked off
a night of colour, music, costumes and glitter.
there isa music, costumes and glitter. there
is a party going on right here. over 200 floats
paraded down sydney polls oxford street from
drag queens the giant bottles of champagne
and lgbt icon cher. but for many, the most
significant float is that of the 78ers, dedicated
to the original activist who marched 40 years
ago in syd ney activist who marched 40 years
ago in sydney and were met with police violence.
it is wonderful, exhilarating to have such
a wonderful audience to look at us and cheer
us and all that. we didn't have any of that
40 years ago. very proud pride march still
glowing
from the yes vote. here in the uk, pubs will
be allowed to stay open late to celebrate
the wedding of prince harry and the american
actress meghan markle. the big day is getting
closer and now pubs will be able to stay open
longer. cheers! on the friday night before
the royal wedding and a saturday night at
golf licensing hours of being extended till
one against the people have more time to raise
a glass to the happy couple. it isa raise
a glass to the happy couple. it is a great
idea, and let people celebrate and bring people
together. to connect people to the royal family
we need to be able to celebrate as well. very
much in favour! it is being all pubs need.
this has happened before, including for the
wedding of the duke and duchess of cambridge
and the queen's 90th birthday. it is the home
secretary who can briefly loosened licensing
laws for special occasions. of course the
royal wedding coincides with this year's fa
cup final on the 19th of may but the government
says there have been no reports of increased
disorder when proper rules have previously
been relaxed in this way. it is all about
community, it is about coming together and
celebrating, whether it is football are wedding
and i think actually it will be a great day
the people and pubs. on friday prince harry
and meghan markle announced over 1000 members
of the public will be invited to the grounds
of windsor castle to join be invited to the
grounds of windsor castle tojoin in be invited
to the grounds of windsor castle to join in
the celebrations and he wedding bells chime.
drinkers will hear a familiar peel through.
bell rings. just a little later than normal.
jessica parker, bbc news. if you would like
any more on both stories, go to our website.
goodbye. hello, thanks forjoining me.
our latest look at how the weather will pan
out in the british isles for the next few
days or so. the good news is the forthcoming
week looks as though it will be nowhere near
as brutal as the weather we have just experienced.
having said that, it will tend to stay really
rather unsettled. nothing unusual for the
time of year. the area of low pressure driving
the weather at the moment is in fact going
to be with us for the rest of the weekend
and on into the start of the forthcoming week.
at least while that area of low pressure is
around we are looking towards the atlantic,
rather than towards the continent, scandinavia
and siberia, where all of that cold weather
came from that has affected so many so very
badly in recent days. and the first signs
of something a little milder is already there
to be had across parts of the far south. not
that much further north though. many more
of you are having to contend with scenes very
much more like that.
there will be a rather wintry flavour to the
start of the day across the northern half
of the british isles. temperatures in the
major towns and cities will be below zero.
as a consequence, there will be a widespread
problem of untreated surfaces with ice. that
does notjust extended in northern half of
the british isles, some spots further south
are covered by met office warnings. having
said that, much of what falls from the skies
during sunday will be watery rather than wintry.
there will be plenty of it as well, eventually
across east anglia and south-east. the north,
the high ground, further wintry showers across
northern and eastern parts of scotland. increasingly,
just beginning to move away from sea level.
no great problems with the fixture there.
manchester city taking on chelsea at the top
of the premier league. the forthcoming week,
as i have tried to reassure you already, you
need some, the snow will become increasingly
confined to the hills
northern britain. things will stay fairly
unsettled. this is a snapshot for monday.
we see further rain close to the centre of
the low pressure down towards the south-western
quarter. there is still some wintriness, particularly
on the higher ground of northern scotland,
elsewhere really not too bad at all as a start
to the week. many more of you will be getting
to work and notice the temperature is beginning
to creep up, nine, ten, 11 degrees or so.
here we are continuing a trend, certainly
across other parts, double figure temperatures.
they are on the way up across northern britain
as well.