welcome to bbc news, broadcasting to viewers
in north america and around the globe. my
name is nkem ifejika. our top stories: tough
words for some us leaders. students from the
school targeted in a mass shooting demand
tighter gun controls. if all our government
and president can do is send "thoughts and
prayers," then it's time for victims to be
the change we need to see. president trump's
national security adviser accuses the syrian
government of using chemical weapons, and
demands action from global leaders. thousands
turn out to show their respects in zimbabwe
as the body of opposition leader morgan tsvangira
returns home. also in the programme: can you
see anything unusual about this picasso? we'll
uncover the mystery hiding behind the masterpiece.
hello.
i'm nkem ifejika, and this is bbc world news.
thousands of people in florida, including
survivors of wednesday's mass school shooting,
have taken part in a rally to demand tighter
gun controls in the united states. the event
took place outside the court building in the
city of fort lauderdale, a short distance
from the school where a former student, nikolas
cruz, killed seventeen people. laura westbrook
reports. chanting: no more! outside the federal
courthouse in fort lauderdale, this was the
message to lawmakers. among the protesters
was emma gonzales, who took cover on the floor
of her school's auditorium as a gunman started
shooting. she had this to say to donald trump.
if the president wants to come up to me and
tell me to my face that it was a terrible
tragedy and how it should never have happened
and maintain telling us how nothing is going
to be done about it, i will happily ask him
how much money he received
from the national rifle association. what
she's referring to is the millions of dollars
the nra has given towards the trump campaign.
on a visit to the hospital where the victims
of the attack are being treated, the president
once again made no mention of guns or gun
control. instead, he says the problem is mental
illness. just a few kilometres south of where
the protest is being held, a gun show is taking
place. in the us, there are as many guns in
circulation as people. the nra is the most
powerful lobbying organisation in the united
states and they have successfully resisted
every move to tighten gun controls. and for
their supporters, it is a fundamental freedom.
when someone infringes a right for persons
in this country to keep and bear arms, then
it's
an infringement on rights and civil liberties.
that is a big problem. we will spend our times
at funerals... but after yet another school
shooting, anger among the younger generation
is rising. in fact, students across the country
are planning a mass walkout of schools in
april, the anniversary of the columbine high
school massacre. they are demanding adults
listen to them and tighten gun control. laura
westbrook, bbc news. in the last hour, president
trump issued a tweet on the fbi and its investigation
into the school shooting. he's suggested that
the fbi missed the signals that the florida
gunman, nikolas cruz, was planning a massacre
at his school because he said the agency is
spending too much time investigating his ties
to russia. he's tweeted that this was not
acceptable and the fbi needed to get back
to basics. president trump's national security
adviser has called on world leaders to hold
the syrian government to account for its continued
use of chemical weapons. speaking at the munich
security conference, hr mcmaster says it is
clear that such weapons are still being deployed.
tensions between moscow and washington have
also been evident at the conference. our chief
international correspondent, lyse doucet,
is in munich. it is not the first time that
senior us officials have accused president
assad's government and its main ally, russia,
are being behind the use of chemical weapons
in this area. we have recently a warning from
the french president, emmanuel macron, saying
there was evidence that they would strike
in retaliation to the use of chemical weapons.
it is not the first time. emmanuel macron,
in his case, so there was no proof what we
have heard from hr mcmaster, he said thatjudging
by public records and by photographs, the
evidence is clear. he did not make clear which
public record or photographs he was referring
to. we do know that time and again, every
time this accusation is made,
the syrian government denies it and they have
responded when there was the warning from
emmanuel macron, faisal mekdad, the deputy
foreign minister, said that the syrian government
did not possess chemical weapons and he described
them as immoral. let's ta ke let's take a
look at some of the other stories making the
news. the israeli air force has carried out
raids in the gaza strip following an explosion
near the border in which four soldiers were
hurt. an israeli military spokesman said six
hamas military targets were hit, including
a tunnel. it's not known if there are any
casualties at this stage. around 100 neo-nazis
have held a torchlit march through the bulgarian
capital sofia, to honour a nationalist leader
who formed an alliance with the nazis during
the second world war. the event, held for
lieutenant-general hristo, lukov, went ahead
despite condemnation from the mayor and two
us congressmen. the march has been held annually
since 2003.
14 people have been killed, including a six-month-old
baby, when a mexican military helicopter,
carrying top officials surveying the damage
from an earthquake, crashed in a small town
in the southern state of oaxaca in mexico.
shuba krishnan has more. it was supposed to
be a military mission to assess damage and
provide support after a shocking 7.2 magnitude
quake. but it all went terribly wrong. the
helicopter carrying mexico's interior minister
and the 0axaca
state governor crashed on top of two minibuses
in a small village not far from the epicentre.
14 people were killed including a six-month-old
baby. remarkably, senior officials on board
survived. the delegation had been touring
0axaca, the epicentre of friday's earthquake.
while no deaths have been reported from the
earthquake itself, it did leave nearlyi million
homes and businesses without power. witnesses
of the helicopter crash say it could have
been a power cuts that played a factor. they
say it circled several times, raising thick
clouds of dust and further reducing visibility.
translation: the entire town was without light,
it was dark. we were happy up there, we were
going to sleep up there, we were all going
to be up there but look what they did. the
governor was supposedly coming to help but
what was the help? the aid we received. this
was the aid? mexican politicians have apologised
for the accident but that won't do much to
ease the pain felt by relatives mourning the
loss of their loved ones. shuba krishnan,
bbc news. the body of zimbabwe's opposition
leader, morgan tsvangirai, has arrived back
in the country following his death from cancer
in south africa earlier this week. he was
65. hundreds of his supporters were at the
airport in harare to pay their respects. our
correspondent in harare is shingai nyoka.
he arrived at the airport where hundreds of
supporters were there to meet him. his body
was then escorted to the military barracks
where it will lie in state until tomorrow.
what we understand is that there will be a
church service at about 12 gmt tomorrow, followed
by a public service, a memorial service on
monday, and then finally his body will be
taken to his village, which is about four
hours outside the capital. he will be laid
to rest there. this is a state assisted funeral,
not a state funeral, in that case he would
have been buried at the national heroes acre.
the supporters were obviously very excited
to have his body back. they almost broke down
the hangar trying to get his body. but zimbabweans
have been
in a very sombre mood, remembering the legacy
that he had. he has been in politics here
in zimbabwe for about 20 years. he has led
the movement for democratic change for all
of that time. he is the figurehead for the
opposition and many people are wondering what
will happen to the opposition now that he
has passed away, given that in about four
months because time the country will be heading
for elections. it is a major departure from
what zimbabweans are used to. under president
robert mugabe, morgan tsvangirai served as
his minister, but it was a very acrimonious
relationship between the parties. what we
have heard at the last few days from the president,
he described him as a son of the soil. they
said they might even consider conferring another
honour on him, the relationship between the
military and the party has always been tenuous.
they hailed him as a man who contributed to
democracy and pushed for free and fair elections
across the country. across-the-board, we have
seen
something that zimbabweans have never really
seen. that is all the political parties coming
together, putting their differences aside
to celebrate the life of morgan tsvangirai.
the british prime minister has called for
a new security treaty with the european union
after brexit, warning that lives could be
at risk without full co-operation. in a speech
in germany, theresa may said new arrangements
over working together should be effective
by next year. the president of the european
commission, jean claude juncker, agreed that
a post-brexit security alliance was necessary,
but said it should be negotiated separately
from other issues, such as trade. our political
correspondent, vicki young, reports from munich.
in defence and security of the uk
is a significant player. the prime minister
hopes that will get her a special deal. she
arrived in munich, keen to lay out britain's
contribution. generous spending on defence
and expertise it wants to share even after
brexit. theresa may urged the eu to take a
practical approach. this cannot be a time
when any of us allow competition between partners,
rigid institutional restrictions or deep-seated
ideology to inhibit our cooperation and jeopardise
the security of our citizens. she's calling
for a new security treaty so that the close
partnership can continue. failure to agree
one would have damaging consequences, she
said. we must do whatever is most practical
and pragmatic in ensuring our collective security.
those who threaten our security would like
nothing more
than to see us fractured. some listening to
this were left bewildered. the brexit decision
from the point of view of us inside the eu
is extremely regrettable. things would be
so much easier if you stayed. so here comes
the questions. applause. mrs may pointed out
that brexit was a democratic decision politicians
should respect. one senior brussels figure
seemed to agree. the commission president,
jean-claudejunker, said the eu wasn't at war
with the uk and didn't want to take revenge
on the british people. he said the security
bridge would be maintained, but you couldn't
mix it up with other issues. conservative
mps attending the conference here believe
the speech is a good starting point for talks.
we've got to start getting into the detail
of this. i think one thing we can do is improve
our offer around defence and security, and
i do think we need to have another look in
the uk as to how we prioritise security. so
it's a pretty familiar message from theresa
may. the uk is leaving the european union
but that doesn't mean that close cooperation
needs to end. and it's a blunt message too,
saying to europe's leaders don't let your
ideology get in the wake
of the safety of our citizens. the government
hopes today's speech will show it's acting
responsibly, not wanting to drag the important
issue of security into fraught brexit negotiations.
vicki young, bbc news, munich. stay with us
on bbc news. still to come: she was famously
linked to an attack on a fellow skater. now,
the story of tonya harding gets the hollywood
treatment. we speak to the film's stars. nine
years and 15,000 deaths after going into afghanistan,
the last soviet troops
were finally coming home. the withdrawal completed
in good order, but the army defeated in the
task it had been sent to perform. malcolm
was murdered. that has a terrible effect on
the morality of the people. i'm terrified
of the repercussions in the streets. one wonders
who is next. as the airlift got under way,
there was no letup in the eruption itself.
lava streams from a vent low in the crater
flowed down to the sea on the east of the
island - away from the town for the time being,
but it could start flowing again at any time.
the russians heralded their new generation
space station with a spectacular night launch.
this is bbc news.
the latest headlines: students from the florida
school where seventeen people were killed
in a mass shooting this week have taken part
in a rally demanding tighter gun controls.
president trump's national security adviser
said it is time the world held syria to account
for using chemical weapons. now, day nine
of the winter olympics in south korea are
under way with no medals up for grabs so far
but here's some of the highlights from day
eight. norway's marit bjorgen has skied her
way into the record books as part of the winning
team in the ladies four by five kilometre
cross country event. she is now the joint
most decorated winter olympian of all time
with 13 medals to her name. and great britain's
lizzy yarnold successfully defended her skeleton
title claiming gold ahead of team-mate laura
deas who got the bronze. which alongside a
bronze for izzy atkin in the ski slopestyle
event marked great britain's most successful
day at a winter olympics.
and in the ski jump poland's kamil stoch retained
his large hill individual title with a leap
of 136 and a half metres. to keep up to date
with the latest action - just go to the bbc
sport website. czech ester ledecka has caused
one of the biggest shocks in winter olympic
history. she swapped her snowboard for a pair
of borrowed skis and then beat the world's
best skiers to win the super-g. it's the first
alpine olympic gold medal for the czechs.
richard mcelvanney reports. ester ledecka
prefers to travel downhill by snowboard and
she is pretty useful on skis as well. not
a lwa ys pretty useful on skis as well. not
always corrode skis, though, she borrowed
these from giant slalom gold-medallist mikaela
shiffrin. faster than she has ever gone at
the super-g and faster than anyone else at
pyeongchang, taking it to one of
the most unexpected goals of the games. so
unexpected that the czech had to check if
she won. and no! what happened ? had to check
if she won. and no! what happened? what happened.
you tell me for that i really don't know what
happened. it was great. ester ledecka is due
to race in the snowboarding parallel slalom
next week and has to decide whether to ski
again in next week's downhill. her rivals
may help she chooses not to and mccullough
schiffer and may wa nt to and mccullough schiffer
and may want her skis back by then. -- mikaela
shiffrin. while many eyes are focused on this
year's winter olympics, one of the most hotly-tipped
films for sunday night's british academy of
film and television awards is ‘i, tonya,‘
based on events linked to the winter olympics
of 1994. it's a biopic about the american
figure skater tonya harding, who became notorious
for her link to an attack on a fellow skater.
margot robbie plays the disgraced tonya, and
allisonjanney plays her mother - both have
received bafta nominations. our arts editor
will gompertz
has been to meet them. i was the best figure
skater in the world at one point in time.
4.8. how do i get a fair shot here? it wasn't
about telling the tonya harding story. the
haters always say, "tonya, tell the truth."
reporter: tonya, how do you feel. . . ? tyres
squeal. everyone has their own truth. there's
the whole, you know, conversation around truth.
we have all these unreliable narrators telling
completely contradictory versions of the exact
same event. i mean, come on! what kind of
friggin‘ person bashes in theirfriend's
knee? who would do that? the juxtaposition
of everyone's different point of view and
story is where the dark comedy comes in, where
you see my character throw a knife at tonya
and then you cut to me saying, "you know,
what family doesn't have their ups and downs?"
i didn't stay home making apple brown betty's.
no. i made you a champion! knowing you'd hate
me for it! that's the sacrifice a mother makes!
i wish i had a mother like me instead of nice!
you cursed me. in the movie, you assault your
daughter on more than one occasion and yet,
her mother in real life denies it happening.
i told her side of the story very well. i
think i - i understood i had to make her a
three-dimensional character. she wasn'tjust
a monster. how old are you, honey? she's a
soft four. having been a figure skater myself,
i know how expensive it is to have custom
skates and have the skating costumes. i know
what it took for my parents to get up at
in the business, do you think the game is
still rigged against women? there's far more
female-driven content, female-led films now
than even when i started - and i haven't even
been doing it this long. i think the next
step is having female storytellers tell those
stories and that's the change that i can see
happening right now. everyone is really making
a conscious effort and i think we will see
the, you know, the result of that over the
next couple of years. but still, is it enough?
no. we still have - the statistics are so
imbalanced, i think it's going to take a while.
but, yeah... new scanning technology has revealed
a painting underneath the famous picasso work
- "a crouching woman". the picture underneath,
is of the catalan landscape and is thought
to have been painted by a student. our science
correspondent pallab ghosh reports. picasso's
crouching woman - worth millions.
a painting from his blue period. but there's
more to it than meets the eye. the conservators
at the gallery analysed it with a new type
of scanner, and this is what they discovered
- underneath it is a painting of the barcelona
landscape by a fellow artist. but turn it
90 degrees and bring back the crouching woman
and you see that picasso has used the landscape
as the basis of his painting. it helps date
the painting. it helps determine where the
painting was made. but it also gives a sense
of the artist with whom a particular painter
was engaging. and i think these insights do
help ask us new and more interesting and more
scientifically accurate questions. the contour
of the hills in the background becomes the
crouching woman's back, and she takes on the
shape and form of the catalan countryside.
until now, only the wealthiest galleries could
afford to scan, and even then, it was only
for great works of art. but the new system
is cheaper and portable, and so can be used
by anyone to find the secrets behind
any painting they want. the mexican muralist
artist... here at the harry ransom center,
the curator has questions about this portrait
of the american composer george gershwin - in
particular, whether a friend in the front
row was painted out and seated further back
because he fell out of favour. so, this figure
here is oscar levant, who was a friend of
george gershwin, but also a rival. and so,
stories have circulated for years that perhaps
he, as the only recognisable figure in the
second row, was perhaps moved - demoted, as
it were - from appearing in the first row.
so that's one of the questions that we can
potentially find out with this technology.
can i take a look? tracy has asked the team
that developed the scanning system to help
her answer that question. they scan each stroke
of the brush, millimetre by millimetre. it's
a collaboration that the team wants to extend
to more galleries. many of these paintings
are waiting to tell their secrets and so,
with the x-ray fluorescent spectrometer, we
can help them talk to us more. the team hopes
that the widespread use of their scanners
will increase our understanding of artists,
their thought processes, and the way they
worked. when kaya day searched for synonyms
for the word "feminine" on thesaurus.com,
she was so disappointed with the limited selection
that she wrote a letter of complaint. now
she says she's trying to get different words
added so that language can catch up with social
consciousness about gender. antonyms include
rough and masculine. don't forget you can
get in touch with me and some of the team
on twitter, i'm @nkemifejika. hello there,
good morning.
it's going to be a bit chilly out there first
thing this morning. clearer skies in many
areas to follow the sunshine that we had yesterday.
but there won't be as much sunshine today
because all this cloud that has been filling
in the atlantic is going to be slowly heading
our way. and we've already seen some of that
cloud arriving across wales and the south-west,
so not as cold here. less reliable cloud elsewhere
means a touch of frost - especially for scotland
and down the eastern side of england, and
maybe some patches of fog too. we are going
to get some milder air eventually today - if
not today, then tomorrow. this envelope of
milder air coming in between these two weather
fronts here and it's this first one that we
need to look at for today because it will
eventually bring more rain and drizzle into
western areas. most places will start the
day dry. there may be some early sunshine
across some eastern parts of england. the
best of the sunshine probably for north-east
scotland. should be a lovely day here. a lot
more cloud spilling our way through the day
and especially in the afternoon, the cloud
thickening up to give some
more rain and drizzle, particularly across
northern ireland. but temperatures probably
around 10 or 11 degrees. ironically, where
it's going to be brighter, it's going to be
cooler towards the north-east of the uk. into
the evening and overnight, well, we find this
rain and drizzle continuing to push its way
eastwards pretty much across the country.
not much rain. there may well be some misty,
murky weather over the hills and a lot of
cloud overnight. so as a result, it's going
to be a much milder night, and temperatures
typically 5 or 6 degrees, so no frost early
on monday morning this time. instead, a different
look to the weather for eastern scotland down
the eastern side of england, where we are
going to have some misty, murky conditions
and some rain and drizzle. if there is any
sunshine, maybe some of these western coasts,
perhaps antrim and down, ahead of some more
rain coming in northern ireland later. but
a mild day - temperatures about 10, maybe
as high as 12 degrees or so. but that mild
air getting squeezed away. colder air is going
to be spilling our way over the coming few
days - whether it comes in from the east or
from the west. and we start tuesday with some
thicker cloud,
some outbreaks of rain down the eastern side
of england, for a time in eastern scotland.
that rain tends to peter out, mind you. more
sunshine for northern ireland and for scotland,
perhaps some other western coasts of england
and wales, but already turning cooler out
towards the east underneath all that cloud.
and that's the way temperatures are going
to be going. it is going to be turning cooler.
high pressure building in over the uk - whether
it is this one from the atlantic or this one
from scandinavia, not a great deal of breeze
out there and where you have some breaks in
the cloud, there may well be some frost in
the outlook. after a mild start to the week
it will gradually turn a bit colder. the chance
of some of easterly winds, but it should be
turning dry.