It's one of the world's greatest engineering wonders the great wall of China
They say it can even be seen from space
It's a military masterpiece that has witnessed hundreds of backwards yet it still holds many mysteries
British writer and Historian William Lindsay has lived in China for 20 years exploring the great [wall] has become his lifetime obsession
Lindsay has spent thousands of days on has walked thousands of kilometers [and]
Is the great [war] really how many years did it take to build?
And why was it built to talk crap on [salary] or Roll to your quarters?
It's only a short trip from beijing to one of China's most popular attractions
Millions of tourists come here every year to see the stone dragon the great wall of China
Most of the people walking on the great war here today will go home and say I've been to the great wall of China
But the great [wall] is not a place it ranges across the sub-continental expanse of [North] China
And along its course
many of the locations seldom visited
And some virtually unknown
in 1987 [busy] fulfilled his childhood dream
He walked on the Chinese war two thousand seven hundred kilometers
Only a few pictures remain from this adventure because his films were repeatedly confiscated foreigners were barred from many parts of China
Those times have long changed
China has opened up to the world and an adventure has turned into a scholar
[Lindsay] now seeks out traces of the [great] [wall] of [China] right across the country
23 years after his first trip he sets off again
during the same
exploring 23 years later is really a testament to the
immensity of
What we call the [great] [wall] of [China]
[will] be [our] [hearts] in the last two-and-a-half decades. I explored the warm or 1700 days
[I've] discovered. It's the world's most famous building, but the least-known there's always something new to discover
there is
there is no single great warm there are lots of words in Northern China built by different dynasties for more than
2,000 years
William Lindsey is taking us to one of the most remote places
2300 Kilometer Drive, West of Beijing to the City of doing one
into the Gobi desert
[clearly] that 75 miles Northwest of don't want
And it's a nice sunny day in the gobi doesn't perfect conditions for exploring the great wall
In the shimmering heat the dark Ribbon along the Horizon at first looks like a mirage, but these really are the remains of a war
literally in the middle of nowhere
Well one of the most precious parts of the [great] [wall] of [China]. This is the hand war hell 2100 years ago
And [I'm] not the first traffic to come here. This is the silk Road
So merchants would come from the deserts in Central, Asia
entering [China] at this point and then
Proceed East to the Heartland of [China]
So it's going to take a closer look
Built over 2,000 years ago this wall looks completely different to the familiar Great [warley] efficient. It's not built of stone
But this construction material has kept its strong for Millennia read and gravel
But who [is] this war meant to protect so far from Civilization?
the Han Dynasty
Rulers wanted to open Their empire to trade with the West
So they secured control of the eastern end of what became known as the silk Road?
the Han Chinese
occupied the vital [if] [she] colony
That runs along the road between them more than steps and the [himalayan] hotels
It's a real border not just between peoples, but between lifestyle
the Nomads of the Step vignettes traditional round tent
They live entirely from their livestock [wandering] over the step they pitch there. Yes, wherever they find grazing land for their herds
after enduring long hard winters in the steps these nomadic warriors ransacked China's Northern provinces
Year after year they killed [road] stealing food and metals everything their lifestyle prevents the producing
The Chinese regarded their empire as the cradle of civilization
According to their confusion philosophy it was the cultural center of the world
Appeasing the Barbarians along the water by trading is out of the question
[all] was too expensive so the harm emperor decided to build a war
How many people were involved in the construction of the harm or no one knows for sure?
Reliable sources quote the calculations presented to the emperor
If one soldier can build three [places] of war in one month than 300 and build three [leap] about one-and-a-Half kilometres
That means a thousand Li were about [500] [30] kilometers would take a hundred thousand men one month to complete
So far so good
and so many
Most of the soldiers were stationed at the towers the towers had a dual use that made the most effective defense
[the] Beacon town behind me was not only the perfect vantage
Point [four] guards on this frontier to watch for the enemy coming from the north [it] was a signaling station
So when the animal was cited this beacon would have been ignited
This is how it worked as soon as a guard spotted nomadic warriors
He transmitted smoke signals by Daylight, or Beacon fires at night
The alarm was communicated along the wall to [Garrison's] located in the Hinterland
How long is the ham war only recently have [Chinese] experts started to find?
Join the local archaeological survey ting
taking part in a national survey
to locate dynasty
A team is heading out into the [gobi] desert. They need a whole summer just to measure this section
At noon the temperature can decline to the 40 degrees celsius?
Today the team is exploring a fortification that lies in the hinterland of the [hardwar]
This could have been a Garrison for support Troops
Today the remains are hardly visible
Right here, and [that's] all you guys hear this tower has a name
it's called half Tower obviously because half the tower is missing the team here today to locate the
Fortifications with GPS and wondering how they're going to measure the height because it's so Crumbly, [Alaska]
needs a [Ma]
Their dog are high challenge you [were] you another Paula [only] all [touchy] you are so that?
You can get that [other] [players] are
Only used for year [and] [will] not cold weather are
So they don't have to have to climb up the tower to measure it. They have a device here
[right] here
Hey the laser rangefinder Connects the data
It will be a Few years before the results of the survey are
summarized and a figure can be given for the length of the harm war
The challenge opens a lot of your body are [organized] [or] so from here to the Jade gates is about
45 50 kilometers
And there are three sections of war that are quite visible
And in between there's virtually nothing although the archaeologists may find traces
Mr.. Young is very little reluctant to give a guesstimate of how many kilometers of hand wall standing
[GPS], team Leader, Mr.
[jung] has given William
directions to a place in the desert where the wall has a unique shape it's a 16 kilometres hike so william is buying provisions for
The trip but don't [want] market
well
Roll Mate would be very good chance in the desert
[yeah]
A lot of what he sees doesn't seem too useful for a desert trick, but he finally finds what he needs
successful shopping trip for 199 also put supply of High-energy foods
directors
Next morning, and find the clock [Lindsay] sets off for the hike
also select
It's 14.4 K so it's about
99 miles or more he's not walking alone in the desert it would be too dangerous
With him is his Chinese friend
El cajon [sun] coming [up] that their GPS says they will reach the unique strip of wall in five hours
[yeah]
It's cool. No, but the Sparse vegetation is [tinder-dry] there hasn't been any rainfall here for months
[then] walking in the featureless landscape can see a solitary tree over
in 87
[I] just had a big [mouth] for the whole country
Basically my journey along the wall from the desert to the sea
Was like that
1700 miles not the ideal [Map] for [Hiking] across desert Grassland
It's nearly noon and the sun is burning, but finally they arrived at the place. They've been looking for there it is
right that
[lasted] [A]
great
Act brand for William it's already worth the trip even the five hours back amazing. Hey
Look at that fantastic
Of all the faces that the great wall of China house, this is the rarest of [them] [off]
This wall is made of wood
He has six layers of branches there
and
And in between minimal use of the gravel, so I'm really glad I've come here today well worth the 10 mile track
Leaving the doing one region and making his way D stand on the ancient silk Road Williams aiming for a town called [John] [Glenn]
The Historic site is five kilometers out of town
And the best view is from the sky
a giant castle guarding the [wall] built in 1539 by judging emperor of the Ming Dynasty
The main Emperor's contempt for the Nomads reached protest proportions with the demand that the character [g]
Standing for Barbarians should be written as small as possible
After the han Dynasty other dynasties rose and fell many of them built walls, but none of any significant length
Me emperor [genius] [ended] the Dragon throne in 1521
He renewed the [hun] tradition established in ancient times
Constructing a long wall of the Northern border with its westernmost point at the jog one pass
[Jaguar] translates as a barrier to the Pleasant Valley and Pleasant Valley means China
This gigantic fault is built in the foothills of the himalayas
In the courtyard the mighty walls form a kind of maze to stop invaders in their tracks
And there's a wonderful legend about its construction
To Avoid wastage of materials prior to construction of the fortress the architect was asked to calculate exactly how many bricks
required be computed
[999999] the Bricks were delivered the fortress built and at the end the chief of works
Confronted the architect with a brick and said this is wasted, but the architect was too smart
He said no I factored that into the equation
That brick should be placed over the portal and it will bring
All the guards in the fortress and all of those travelers passing under its portals good fortune
600 Years later the Leftover Brick still remains
[yeah]
Next to the fort is the starting point of the wall constructed by the [way]
This wall has nothing in common with the brick and stone
[it's] made of rammed the [loads] more than 400 years old and still in good shape and [its] still wide enough to walk
[yeah]
On his walks along the Walls [William] [Lindsay] soon Learned. He could count on receiving warm hospitality from the farmers among the wedding
Before coming to China my family and friends were very concerned in
1987 going to [China] the big
Communist country on the other side of the world all the people going to be friendly
And I didn't have a support crew with me on [dependent] on Farmers. [I] discovered very early on the farmers were my
great
allies even with very little [Chinese]
But a lot of sign language and smiling [I] got what I needed food water shelter without them
I couldn't have been successful Asean come on
I seea even if many is unkind understand why a foreigner should be so interested in the wall
Then this is no monument, but simply a part of the village and one with a perfectly practical use
I was asking my er the these holes in the wall. I thought they were nasty but in fact
Previously the farms were right up against the wall, so [they're] wooden
Beams going into the wall, but the great wall experts the cultural heritage protection authorities
requested the Farmers to
Destroy those buildings and move back in [order] in order to protect the national heritage if you want to know how many
Dynasty [Mason's] constructed their [wall] more than 400 years ago [what] you have to do is keep your eyes open
even today
Chinese Farmers build walls of the same way their ancestors did they tempt the earth in a wooden case [if]
temp put layer on layer
They even sing the traditional folk songs passed down from their forefathers
A house is not complete without a wall around it
[says] an old Chinese proverb
My friend Tran is building this wall to and closed his compound, so this is the final piece of work
and
This is embedded in Chinese
Architectural tradition
whether it's a compound
For a village or a kingdom it must be enclosed
completely safe
They built up most of the men wore just like this is a [rounder] [swore]
Imagine how many billion [birds] it took?
[Georgia] guns on each [Unger] Tower 10 sure
Busy Long-ago
Oh, I hated [husband] the singing is an important part of the work. It keeps all the rappers
And staff the beat
So another [Lauren] step going along the wall [get] into a rhythm
and
the actual content
or
I've been trying to 23 here is where this guy has [a] really [heavy] [accent]
[it's] a bit difficult, but that it's definitely a kind of wrap
[it] changes the words and occasionally hear them chuckle
So I think [he] gets a little dig in about those that are kind of falling behind in
Distance or maybe he can tell by the [third's] if someone is answered
This group of about twenty farmers mostly women took a day to erect about 27 meters of war
We don't know if their ancestors could have worked better or faster
But we do know they would have used the same materials and tools
except [for] the tractors carrying the clay
and the cell phones [by] [Dover]
[Scylla], Ola
[yeah]
On his Journey along the Walls of China
Williamses looking eastwards out of the [He-she] corridor and turning North along the great wall of the ming Dynasty
into the [great] [gloop] of the [Yellow] [River] the cradle of China's civilization
This has always been the Gateway for the Nomads to Enter China
Here the wind and weather have done their worst the wall and its towers can still be made out on the cracks of the river
The Garrison Forts with the outpost of this defensive outer warm today. They use is strictly [non-military]
[yeah]
[ok]
[I] love staying in the countryside
This building. It's made of thick blocks of limestone and on the roof this stuff when you come here winter
[no] good method for keeping you warm see this
[it's] not that it's called the Camp [Kng]
And they put the fuel and here light it can do the cooking here
You've got a nice warm bed for the night
So I got full board and lodging
Breakfast morning and dinner this evening and lunch coming up soon for less than ten dollars
[ha]
I should apologize for the slurping it's part and parcel of eating in China
Considered sound of an appreciation
The ingredients of the Lunch [William] is appreciating today also the reason the Nomads raided the land of the yellow River throughout
the 16th Century
[yeah] in the year 1549 the barbarians come to plunder
[yeah]
[redick] cavalry to a virtual standstill at the new Border war that shoe and food
The wall stands fast the Nomadic troops are unable to capture the [Chinese] ground
Does this mean defeat [you]?
The Barbarians do not give up the message for the Chinese
They will attack beijing the capital
By marching [east] the Nomads Army finds its way around the wall thus avoiding the ming emperor's Elaborate border fortifications
No one had suspected the Nomads could cross the natural barrier the Mountain range North Vision
Back in 1550 the Nomads did not meet with any serious opposition on their way south
They terrorized beijing suburbs for three days
They demanded trading rights
Leaving the Forbidden City
untouched before drawing back to the steps
After a short period of trading the ming emperor started building a wall of stone not of beijing
between the 15 fifties and
1644 it reached a length of at least
1,200 kilometers the stone Dragon the Chinese great [wall] as the world knows it today
How many people were needed to build it?
official figures are rare but in some
Inaccessible sections of the wall there are still stone tablets in [grave] with texts that could give us that information
Good
I'm hoping this stone is going to tell me something about when this wall was built
How many people were involved and mentioned some place names from here the inscription looks very faint, but we have a ladder
Master Artisan Mr.. [Hull], and with his simple tools. We're going to
Copy the stone and produce a rubbing which hopefully will reveal the full content of the tablet
This ancient Chinese copying technique starts with blowing a sheet of paper onto the template simply with water
This is step number one step number two
Dads are translates literally as typing characters are using a brush
[and] he's hammering the paper into the carvings
the higher
parts of the paper
Will be blackened and the lower parts that have gone into the characters and any
design along the Edges there will remain white
After three hours of sponging and drying Mr.. [cole] presents his peace of God
It looks like a blueprint for an old archive document
[are] [all] [I] am Monica and helps william translate the ancient Chinese characters?
Which today have the anybody can read?
our
diggity
dog
[brought]. [I] want to draw add up
[hard] just have bad [won't] [buy] [a] book
That was younger all [filled] up [yunyun] [get] this stone is telling us that [to]
military officials in charge of
1100 Families
put in the effort to build
250 yards of war in the autumn of 1579 so in terms of very simple
arithmetic productivity, we're talking about four persons per family
4,500 people working for eight to ten weeks in the autumn of 1579 to build that
[we're] [a] stamped Earth Walls were built by untrained surface or presents this project required special knowledge
hundreds of Master Builders and skilled engineers
Thousands of Stone cutters and tens of thousands of Mason's were recruited to build the war
And another factor, led to the costs rising exponential
[Tamped] Earth Walls were built using materials available on-site
The material for the new [and] to be manufactured before use
The Chinese [had] devised a network of Brick kilns set up near the construction sites one of these sites was found by local farmers
and inspected by professor 12 new curator of the Great war Museum in [showing] [1]
so at this location they discovered around 60 brick kilns and it ranks as the
best Production center of Bricks
Preserved along the whole length of the great [war] and it's estimated that each kill
could fire five thousand bricks now given that there are 60 kilns in this valley the
production of this [Center] Alone would be equal to
three hundred
thousand bricks per month industrial scale production
Then is now mass production is one thing, but it's a different matter to Transport the product to where it's needed
logistics
[yeah]
now key question very interesting question is how did they move all the bricks of the
One show need to add a [normally]
Challenges Sham [Mk]. Coming up on why, Georgia track down John
Show me again there is almost no historical record to answer this question
But professor one has his theory
[should] hear something people may have carried a few bricks on their backs like this
And also it's been suggested a herd of goats could have carried a lot of bricks up there quite effectively
War two bricks on the back of the goat and the bricks are joined together
With rope so the goat is quite balanced as it's moving up the mountain
[yeah]
Even without brakes on your back. It's a hard slog up to the wall, but it's worth it
Hardly any tourists make it to this isolated section
[yeah]
Every time I come up here on this trials a spare for the builders
Had to heave [porsche] all of this building material of hell these blocks all of this trick
Sometimes Bizarre route taken by this war has led many experts to believe that more than just defensive
Considerations were in play here and for generations. [the] Chinese have followed the practice of fun [Schwee]
the teachings of the wind and water
function where experts were probably
Concepted and debate before the building of the wall to make sure that the forces of nature would work in its favor
Spending his days alone on the wall, [Nz] imagines. How the soldiers must have suffered here cut off from the world
enduring wins and foul weather
Squeezed into bear and cramped quarters for months on [N]
[yeah]
Finally this war is a monument to the closed world view of the empire
[is] circumscribed their universe and excluded everything that was for?
Often scratching around in this rubble, you can find bits of pottery sure what this stone asst
Students [pointing] system [may] [be] a broken it
[ok] [yeah]
[ok]
might be
that
is
A
stone bomb
That would have been packed with gunpowder
A mud seal [refuse]
And the towns like this was all just packed with these maybe fifty or hundred
to be
dropped off the wall when the tower was attacked
That's a really good find
[yeah], 320 kilometers further east we find another example of living history
should trigger some holy lady [Eagle] [hollister] like the bottle and [ordered] [a] yellow for
This is John hirsh on his ancestors built a wall here four [hundred] [and] [forty] years ago
and close by
Towers have other family names like the chant our the wang towel the law tower, so we're here
We have the family history of the great [wall] still living on
440 Years after it was built
Even today they still worship their ancestors by celebrating ancient festivals
[man], the Pig was closed yesterday should be quite nice fresh [for]
It would have been a rare moment of relaxation and abundance in a hard life
As the oldest member of his family Mr.. General makes the sacrifice to his ancestors and burns incense sticks
[yeah], [ok]
[any] the living generations of the junk family bowed to the dead and to their own great mystery?
The Village families had to look after and feed the soldiers in the tablets
There take away food service survives to this day
Janish and Farmer down in transient Village prepared some delicacies for me
Munch on up here after my hike
And it's amazing to think that 400 years ago
Guards [Garrison] up on the wall will be sent these
[lobbying] by their families
so look
It's a kind of pasty
caps Fresh in one of these large Oak leaves
[you] can see the leaf prints on the pastry
[ever] taste
Hmm
follow tribes
Kind of try and try this hamburger. Maybe the original Chinese takeaway for those up on the wall
[yeah]
by
1644 just short of a hundred Years of construction the most impressive defensive wall ever made by man was finished
however, it was not one single [great] [wall] it comprised a system of several Defense lines from the Mountains to
the sea
In 2009 after a national survey of the ming wall Chinese officials announced that the total length is
8850 Kilometers
This is the end Chug one meaning Mountain see parts
the Chinese like in the [main] great [walls] [were] [dragons] sneaking across their land and here it comes to a
Geographical and that's all dragons had [of] the [Loc]
Not far from this location in 1644 the commander of Shanghai [guan] faced his biggest challenge
An event which [led] to the end of the great wall functioning as a national defense
Professor one is taking William to the gates and walls in the outskirts of shang one
This is the place where the great [wall] story came to an end
The construction of the great wall led to the financial and strategic
collapse of the Ming Dynasty
Revolts broke out everywhere in the Empire
An Army of Rebel peasants marched on beijing where they toppled the emperor?
Then on to Shanghai [Guan] the last stronghold of the ming Empire
But a mighty army had risen from the steps heading for the middle Kingdom the Manchus
Caught in between some [Wii]. He was the general in command of the fortress of [suge] one
Now he was under siege
What would he do this was a powerful Garrison that wasn't strong enough to fight off attackers on [two] friends
[yeah]
[lightyear] not having to do about
[that] [beef] when professor want to know about tells [when] [you're] [missing] the solution he found [on] gravity for the old one so trapped between
Two enemies commander was angry. [I] knew he couldn't defeat them both, so we came up with a plan to offer a
alliance Treaty with the Manchus in the North and the two armies joined and
Confronted the [peasant] rebel army and they defeated them the wall is only as strong as the men who guard it
Genghis Khan is supposed to have said his successes from the steps the Manchus would have agreed with
80,000 Manchu soldiers pass through this gate
and answered
the
Heartland of China the Manchus founded a new Dynasty which in effect ruled over the Middle Kingdom until Nineteen Twelve
They call themselves [ching] meaning the pure
And the great wall is of no use anymore
But its story did not come to an end
Even today nobody knows how long all the great walls of China really are
There are still many more walls and stories to be discovered
And [William] [Lindsay] will not stop walking the great wall until he knows them
I don't think in future and so many people will be organized in such a methodical way
To create something that was not just history that not just fell apart
[but] is left as part of the geography of China and the world
Certainly in future there are going to be new wonders
communications longer life exploring planets
But in terms of blood sweat and tears the Great wall of China
I think is the ultimate that's why I'm continuing to understand