zimbabwe's military is in full control of
the country.
robert mugabe, president for nearly a0 years,
remains under house arrest.
climate change is inevitable, even if we drastically
cut co2 emissions.
a new environmental report makes grim reading.
selling for $400 million, that is the better,
and this is sold! -- thatis the better, and
this is sold! -- that is the bid.
the world's most expensive artwork.
a long-lost painting by leonardo da vinci
sells at auction for $400 million.
the soaring cost of living in zimbabwe - could
the dark days of hyperinflation be returning?
plus africa's richest woman, the boss of angola's
state oil company, is sacked - so what now
for isabel dos santos? a very warm welcome
to the
programme, briefing you on all you need to
know in global news, business and sport. and
you can be part of the conversation today.
we are asking for your reaction to the da
vinci frenzy - the 500-year-old painting sold
for $400 million, smashing all records.
are you amazed or appalled? is it worth it
or wealth gone mad?
your comments to hashtag #bbcthebriefing.
we start the programme in zimbabwe.
south africa's defence and state security
ministers have arrived in the country, and
they now hope to hold talks with president
mugabe and army leaders, following the military’s
seizure of power.
mr mugabe remains under house arrest, although
the military says he is safe.
it denies staging a coup, instead claiming
to be acting against "criminals" surrounding
the president.
the african union has demanded an immediate
return to constitutional order.
0ur correspondent anne soy joins me now from
zimbabwe.
we've heard that there's a calm but tense
atmosphere on the streets of zimbabwe's capital,
harare.
it is hard to know what will happen next.
that is right.
you get the sense that the military is controlled
listening to the media here.
many of the story is talking about them, the
youth league, or the ruling party, zanu-pf,
pledging allegiance to the burko.
not much mention of robert mugabe, except
for the move by the military, in their words,
to deal with criminals around
the president.
grace mugabe, his wife, her whereabouts is
unknown, along with that of the former vice
president, emmerson mnangagwa.
you mentioned both grace mugabe and the vice
president, both of whom we don't know where
they are, butjust august through the politicking
that led to this disaster.
it is clear now that it has a split between
the ruling zanu-pf that has brought zimbabwe
to the current situation where the president,
rod mcgarvie, even though the military says
he remains in charge, remains under house
arrest.
his wife, grace mugabe, as being ambitious,
very keen to succeed him, and last week, the
vice president, emmerson mnangagwa, was sacked,
and he fled out of the country as a result
of that.
but he also vowed to come back, and make sure
that he takes
control of the country.
we still do not know where he is, but what
is clear now is that the army chief, constantino
chiwenga, is with him.
thank you for at that.
all the latest is on a website.
-- our website.
that's bbc.com/news.
but now, let's look at a study which suggests
many impacts of climate change are already
inevitable, even if the world radically cuts
carbon dioxide emissions immediately.
an international research programme called
helix says that sea level rises of at least
several
tens of centimetres will "definitely happen".
andy moore reports.
this latest report has been presented to an
international conference on climate change
in bonn, where world leaders have already
begun to gather.
whatever they can do to restrict carbon, dockside
restriction -- restrict carbon dioxide restriction,
climate change cannot be avoided.
researchers can say with some confidence that
half a million people in low-lying bangladesh
will be affected by rising sea levels.
in a worst-case scenario, with rising emissions,
africa could reach 12 million by the end of
the century.
some tropical areas already suffer levels
of heat bringing a very high risk of human
harm, so-called heat stress.
the researchers say that with two degrees
warming, large areas of the subcontinent and
africa would get these conditions.
rainfall and river levels are hard to predict,
but scientists say they are
confident they will be increased flooding
on some major rivers, even if emissions are
strictly reduced.
and there is no sign of that happening at
the moment.
the conference has already been told that
global emissions of carbon dioxide, continue
to rise.
-- dioxide, continue to rise.
-- dioxide continue to rise.
a lot of thatis dioxide continue to rise.
a lot of that is being attributed to the chinese
economy.
let's brief you on some of the other stories
making the news.
the greek prime minister, alexis tsipras,
has announced a state of national mourning
for those who died in flash flooding that's
killed at least 15 people near athens. local
officials say the floods, which brought torrents
of reddish mud flowing through three towns,
are unprecedented.
homes have been inundated and roads destroyed.
russian officials say a new law which will
categorise overseas media outlets as "foreign
agents" could affect the us government broadcaster
voice of america.
russia's lower house of parliament backed
the measure, which was drawn up after washington
ordered the russian state tv channel, rt,
to register
as a foreign agent.
astronomers say they've discovered a planet
about the size of earth, with a mild climate
which could harbour life.
called ross 128b, it's a mere 11 light years
away.
researchers believe the planet's temperature
could range from -60 to 20 celsius, making
it a promising place to search for life beyond
earth.
are they out there?
life, is it out there, that is what i mean.
a 500-year-old painting of christ by leonardo
da vinci has been sold in new york for a record
price of $400 million.
after eighteen minutes of frenzied bidding,
this was the moment the hammer went down on
the artwork, which is known as salvator mundi,
or saviour of the world.
we moved to the alarm of da vinci,
the salvator mundi... we moved to the alarm
of da vinci, the salvator mundi.
.. christie suggested that salvator mundi
would sell for about Â£76 million.
they knew that was likely to be exceeded co
nsta ntly. knew that was likely to be exceeded
constantly.
nobody could get how come the way.
dating from around 1506, the image ofjesus
christ is thought to have been created for
the french royal family.
disastrously restored in 1958, it was auctioned
in luck than for a mere Â£45. -- in london.
at that time, most experts thought was based
on and leonardo, not by the man himself.
last night, the tension was obvious.
$100 million was reached quickly, than $200
million.
$190 million is dead.
$200 million.
$200 million is dead.
that broke the previous record, held by picasso's
women of algiers.
i am selling at $240 million.
can you give me $290 million alex i thought
so.
the -- trended million dollars.
-- trended million dollars.
the buyer on the phone was tempted to the
extraordinary final amount.
the 100 million dollars as the bid, and the
pieces sold.
-- $300 million.
the sale chose the importance of rarity. this
could be the last leonardo to average auction,
and was half a millennium after his death,
he assured us of the greatest star in the
art world.
so we asked you what you think of this.
a report? are you amazed ? what you think
of this.
a report? are you amazed? is this just a normal
sort of process in terms of fine art, the
fact that it is so
rare... tyrrell paul is getting in touch with
us from the united states and he has said
that it is more than many countries are worth.
that is in the same number in his opinion.
-- tall paul. jon says he does not believe
you.
somebody else has said whether bitcoin is
worth $7,000 or something to bet, it is to
be believed.
and facebook is more valuable than general
electric and exxon mobil, so this is the way
that things are going.
then others to say they have been better.
that was once you from me.
many of you are just saying that you are appalled.
then we have somebody saying that they don't
know about it, but it is the same model as
the mona lisa, said many comments coming in
from you.
coming up on business briefing, we'll be looking
at the economic
backdrop to the events in zimbabwe - amid
reports of soaring inflation despite the official
figures.
and another big story in africa, the continent's
richest woman has been sacked from herjob.
the president of angola, joao lourenco, has
fired the head of the country's state oil
company sonangol.
isabel dos santos is the billionaire daughter
of former presidentjose eduardo dos santos,
and africa's richest woman, with a net worth
of over $3 billion.
president lourenco, known asjlo, has promised
to tackle corruption.
amrita sen is here from energy aspects.
this is quite an interesting story, isn't
it? we apple was arrested zimbabwe, and this
is another key african economy, and this will
have big economic applications.
usually.
she took over a while ago, and there
was criticism of possible nepotism.
the father has obviously ruled the country
for 38 years.
but the oil community was quite positive about
her, because she has been a businesswoman.
sonangol has been struggling.
they had been deteriorating the finance and
the oil prices crash.
she was supposed to restructure the company
and turn it around, but then, of course, when
she got into power, projects started slipping,
and she said it could take five years to restructure.
in the meantime, what is this mean for the
energy sector? within angola, this political
wrangling, this is the world's biggest oil
company, isn't it? actually have a lot of
problems with the finances.
and angola has really suffered.
they have had a lot of new projects come online,
but diplomats have been declining so quickly
that production has not been going anywhere.
so this is an
attempt to fast forward some of the reforms
that need to happen.
whether it happens or not is a separate thing,
but that is the attempt right now, very much.
0k, thank you very a much indeed.
and amrita will be back soon with us for the
new -- news briefing.
please keep the discussion going in regards
to the painting.
still to come this morning, roger federer
is through to the last four at the atp finals
in london, beating alexander zverez, his junior
by 16 yea rs. alexander zverez, his junior
by 16 years.
that and more in the sports briefing.
berliners from both east and west linked hands
and danced round their liberated territory.
and, with nobody to stop them, it wasn't long
before the first attempts were made to destroy
the structure itself.
it's keeping the candidate's name always in
the public eye that counts.
success or failure depends not only on public
display but on the local campaign headquarters
and the heavy routine work
of their women volunteers.
yasser arafat, who dominated the palestinian
cause for so long, has died.
the palestinian authority has declared a state
of mourning for the leader who symbolised
his people's hopes for independent statehood.
in the wake of the colombian volcano disaster,
rescue teams are trying to reach thousands
of survivors who managed to clamber onto rooftops
and trees above the sea of mud. after 17 years
of discussion, the result was greeted with
an outburst ofjoy.
women ministers who'd long felt only grudgingly
accepted amongst the ranks of clergy suddenly
felt welcomed.
you're watching the briefing.
0ur headlines: a new report is warning that
climate change is inevitable even if we drastically
cut co2 emissions.
zimbabwe's military is in full control of
the country.
robert mugabe - president for nearly 40 years
-
remains under house arrest.
let's stay with that now: laura westbrook
has this report.
what would have been unthinkable only a few
weeks ago has happened: robert mugabe, the
world's oldest leader, has lost control of
the country he has ruled for 37 years.
the military denied staging a coup, but it
is clear that robert mugabe is no longer calling
the shots.
zimbabwe's ruling party, the zanu-pf, are
emphatic.
president mugabe is still in power.
he's the man in charge of zimbabwe, officially,
right now.
a lot has happened.
but what has happened is a not coup.
the language is important, and key regional
block, the african union, has given its full
support to the country's legal situations.
to the country's legal institutions.
translation: the military has assured asked
that this is not a coup d'etat. the african
union is against any unconstitutional change
of government.
the president still has his supporters, especially
in rural areas.
but in the capital, harare, news of his house
arrest has been welcomed.
translation: i want to thank the generalfor
removing this tyrant. he was ruling this country
like it belongs to his family.
this boils down to an internal power struggle
within the governing zanu-pf. 0n the one side,
this man, emmerson mnangagwa, who was fired
last week from his position as vice president.
0n the other, mugabe's wife, grace mugabe,
known as "gucci grace" for her at extravagant
spending, and one of the most powerful politicians
in the country.
it is believed that her being groomed to succeed
robert mugabe is what sparked the takeover.
the military has begun to arrest those close
to her.
there has to be a transition away
from robert mugabe but it has to be through
a process that makes the government credible.
zimbabwe is waking up to a country that has
changed dramatically.
but whether it is the change they had been
hoping for is far from clear.
laura westbrook, bbc news.
50,000 children are expected to die in yemen
this year according to the charity save the
children.
who's the rebels -- houthi.
the coalition tried to restore the government.
in the second of his special report, clive
myrie has been to the frontline were fierce
fighting is continuing.
the city sums up the dystopian
nightmare.
no one seems to be in control here.
rubbish piles up in the street.
it feels the local can now instead of water,
much of it a cts now instead of water, much
of it acts of human excrement.
colorado is rampant.
-- cholera.
0n the main highway, running north to south,
is the southern battlefield.
neither side is making any significant territorial
game.
the fighting simply grinds on with civilians
in ever to be caught in the middle.
for the saudi let coalition, air power
has not proved decisive and is not winning
the day.
their military intervention has become stuck,
it is bogged down.
any kind of victory seems a long way.
few in yemen have the luxury of memory that
do not include a time of war.
through britain's colonial era, communism,
civil war and now the proxy struggle of regional
powers that see saudi arabia so prominent
here.
this is what is left of a department store,
smashed by an air strike.
after all the destruction and lies loss, this
warlike most modern conflicts will only come
to an end with a political solution and, at
the very least that requires the yemeni themselves
to come togetherfor requires the yemeni themselves
to come together for the greater good but
the chances of that happening are as remote
as they have ever been so it seems yemen's
pain is destined to endure.
all the malnourished
children are victims of grand designs.
the manoeuvrings of the middle east to a place
from tehran to ridyard.
yemen is stuck in the middle.
born into the world, war babies. will they
ever have peace?
here's our briefing on some of the key events
happening later.
we begin in seoul where the world anti-doping
agency has just decided to maintain its suspension
of russia.
the agency will give more details about it
at 7 gmt. then around midday in london the
chairman of the old vic theatre will give
a briefing on the findings of the investigation
into allegations concerning the conduct of
kevin spacey during his tenure as artistic
director.
and later on in germany it's the deadline
for germany's political parties to agree how
to form the basis of a new coalition in the
wake of septembers inconclusive elections.
sport, now and peru have claimed
the 32nd and final place at next year's world
cup in russia.
they've beaten new zealand 2-0, in lima, in
the second leg of their intercontinental playoff,
and also 2-0 on aggregate.
jefferson farfan and christian ramos scored
the goals, as peru qualified for the world
cup for the first time since 1982. earlier,
australia beat honduras 3-1 in sydney to reach
their fourth successive world cup finals.
and now here's the rest of today's sport briefing
with sarah mulkerrins.
hello i'm sarah mulkerrins with your sport
briefing for thursday.
roger federer is already through to the last
four at the atp finals in london, but can
he keep up his winning ways against marin
cilic later? and we'll tell you about the
iranian weight lifter putting his olympic
gold medal up for auction.
roger federer is the strong favourite to finish
the way he started it - by winning.
the world number two faces marin cilic later
in his last group match, as he aims for yet
another atp finals title.
he's already through to the semi-finals on
saturday and, if he wins the tournament, it
would be his 96th career title.
alexander zverev has a long way to go to match
that record - the german plays jack sock in
thursday's other match, with a place in the
last four for the winner of that.
europe's top golfer for the year will be decided
over the weekend as the race to dubai reaches
it's climax. and there's three players firmly
in the hunt.
england's tommy fleetwood and justin rose
are the leading contenders, although masters
champion, sergio garcia, could pip both of
them to the title if he wins the season-ending
dubai world championship, which gets underway
on thursday.
no matter what position you are in,
you are starting off with the guys you are
starting off with the guys you have around
so it is great for people to watch.
i will enjoy the challenge.
it is a bit of a dogfight towards the end
of the year and i am looking forward to it..
nba fans are in for a real treat later, the
best of the west will face the leaders in
the east, as golden state warriors take on
the boston celtics. and the celtics are on
a roll, their win over the brooklyn nets,
on tuesday was their 13th in a row.
boston have won more nba championships than
any other team but you have to go back to
2008 when they last came out on top. in case
you missed it, if you're a rugby union fan
and really organised, well, you can start
planning your trip for the 2023 world cup.
this was one of the surprise stories on wednesday,
as france was announced as the host.
not many saw it coming,
as south africa were expected to win the vote
after an independent review recommended they
stage the tournament.
ireland also missed out, as world rugby president,
bill beaumont, declared france as hosts after
a secret ballot by the council in london.
it probably won't come as a huge surprise
to hear that italy manager, gian piero ventura,
has been sacked.
it follows their failure to qualify for the
world cup.
a 1-0 aggregate defeat to sweden on monday
sealed italy's fate - meaning they won't play
on football's biggest stage for the first
time since 1958. and, after being given his
marching orders, ventura complained that he
lost only two games in two years.
now team celebrations are always good value
on social media, and tim cahill led the ones
in australia's dressing room as they qualified
for a fourth successive world cup.
here's what he posted after their win against
honduras,
on wednesday.
he was back from injury for that second leg.
he also scored twice in their asian play-off
win over syria.
another image which has been getting lots
of clicks comes from iranian weightlifter
kianoush rostami.
he's putting his rio 2016 gold medal up for
auction, to raise money for the victims of
last week's earthquake near the iran-iraq
border.
as always, you can get all the latest sports
news at our website - that's bbc.com/sport.
but that is your sport briefing for now.
your business briefing is next.
i will see you soon.
hi there.
for many of us it is going to be another pretty
cloudy start to the day on thursday, but there
will be some significant weather changes,
because this cold front is going to be sliding
its way southwards as we go on
through the day and behind that we're going
to see the skies turning much brighter with
much more in the way of sunshine.
early on thursday, but whether around scotland.
a cloudy start to the day the many and fog
patches for some.
it is an improving weather picture as we go
through the day.
the land of rain chased by much sunnier skies.
the rain and moving away from northern ireland
and heading into wales where the rain can
still be quite heavy.
some gaps in the cloud, maybe a few sunny
spells across south-west england and the midlands
but for east anglia and south-east england,
a great and missed the start to the day with
a few fog patches knocking around.
sunshine moving in quickly during thursday
morning at across both northern ireland and
scotland but
not entirely dry in scotland, showers in the
north-west.
showers giving him by a strengthening north-westerly
wind.
a few spots of rain in the north-west.
not much left on it by the time it reaches
london. in the sunnier skies, down goes the
temperatures.
then, thursday evening, the rain clears away
from south-east england.
fear skies which is a recipe per a cold night.
head to the countryside, a widespread frost
across england and wales.
a very cold start to the day.
friday will be a decent kind of day with plenty
of sunshine.
some showers affecting northern and western
parts of scotland.
temperatures are bit below par for
the some of year, 7- ten.
the weekend, sunny spells, a few showers around
on sunday with quite a chilly wind at times
as well.
hello. this is business briefing.
i'm sally bundock. here are the headlines:
the soaring cost of living in zimbabwe - could
the dark days of hyperinflation be returning?
plus a desert oasis with a difference.
the uae plans to colonize mars within a century
and grow lettuce.
yes, you are hearing me correctly.
we'll bring you all the details from the dubai
air show. and on the markets despite a downbeat
day for wall street the night before, asia
is riding higher with japan up by almost a
percent.