it's a mystery continent at the bottom of the earth
of the world
And the single largest mass of ice on Earth.
Earth
for longer than humans have walked the
planet ice has dominated Antarctica
but what about the future. "ice melts from
this continent...
...Sea Level goes up."
as earth gets warmer what will happen to
Antarctica. "We're going into uncertain
lands uncertain future.
how will the earth respond?"  Today a
pioneering team is searching for answers,
with a bold new plan and a revolutionary
new machine no one has ever drove through
an  ice (unintelligable) and I present these challenges
they must drill down nearly a mile and
more than 20 million years deep into
Antarctica's ancient history in this
unforgiving place it's never been done
before it's quite amazing when you think
about where we are and what we're doing
anything can go wrong at any minute the
stakes are high because the secret to
Earth's future lies buried in
Antarctica's past right now on nova
secrets beneath the ice
it's the coldest windiest driest and
most desolate landscape on the planet
with few permanent residents except
penguins and seals this frosty cotton
appears locked in a perpetual Ice Age a
colossal cloak of ice covers almost
every inch of land and in some places
the ice is so thick and so heavy it
depresses the Earth's crust almost half
a mile some people call it Earth's
freezer but scientists call Antarctica
the ice
Antartica plays a fundamental role in
the way the earth functions for polar
researchers Antarctica is a giant
laboratory more than one and a half
times the size of the United States and
home to 90% of all the ice in the world
anything that happens down here anything
that changes will affect the rest of the
world most people don't think that
change in Antarctica matters to them but
when we look at New York City and we
looked at it's in front of the ocean it
matters
what would happen if all of Antarctica's
ice were to melts
antarctica melts sea level goes up
twelve stories in New York City sea
levels would rise by more than 150 feet
flooding coastal cities displacing
hundreds of millions of people that
would be a change that you could see
from space earth would look different in
any case even a loss of just 10% of
Antarctica's ice would be catastrophic
it would raise the sea level over there
in Manhattan about 19 feet right up
along the edge big sections of Brooklyn
would be underwater certainly the
Mediterranean some of my favorite cities
like Venice would look very different
tens of millions of people would have to
be relocated to be almost different
different planet if sea level changes in
the climate around the coastal regions
change it's going to affect the climate
where you live it's going to affect the
things you can you can grow is going to
affect how you have you live there may
be a list of things in store that come
as a result of raising sea levels that
we haven't even thought about yet could
this be our fate is Antarctica heading
for a major meltdown if so it may happen
over centuries but it could already be
starting because the climate is changing
and it's changing because burning fossil
fuels has increased the level of carbon
dioxide in the atmosphere today we have
something that's completely man-made and
that is the addition of carbon dioxide
and put into the atmosphere by humanity
by us carbon dioxide is a greenhouse gas
it prevents the sun's heat from escaping
I'm in the Brooklyn Botanic Garden in a
greenhouse greenhouses there are
basically like heat motels
where the sun's rays can come in and
they get trapped inside the greenhouse
they can't get out
so like glass in a greenhouse gases like
carbon dioxide trap solar energy in our
atmosphere but now those levels are
increasing the result is our earth is
now warming up and the ice is melting
both in Antarctica and the Arctic in the
north there's two clear signals in the
Arctic Ocean you have lots of floating
ice and not sticking around through the
summer
that's one sign of it getting warmer the
other side the edges of the Greenland
ice sheet are changing and the loss of
Greenland's ice is now speeding up in
August 2010 and iceberg four times the
size of Manhattan broke off the edge of
Greenland
but Antarctica has nearly ten times as
much ice as Greenland and in the past
decade alone rising temperatures have
caused giant pieces of coastal ice to
shrink or crumble polar researchers fear
that this could be just the beginning of
a chain reaction but have Antarctica's
ice sheets ever collapsed before that's
what an international team of geo
detectives wants to find out here we
actually have some running water some
melt water coming out of the ice to get
a more precise picture of Antarctica's
future they plan to dig deep for answers
in the past with a giant drill by
drilling into areas around the Erika
we're able to perceive a history that
has an impact for where we're headed as
a planet Antarctica was not always
locked in a deep freeze 160 million
years ago it was part of an enormous
supercontinent closer to the equator at
the time earth was much warmer than
today and fossil evidence suggests this
giant landmass was a tropical habitat
teeming with Dinosaurs eventually the
supercontinent broke apart and
Antarctica drifted south as Earth was
getting colder falling carbon dioxide
levels and powerful ocean currents
cooled the isolated continent even
further and then around 34 million years
ago ice slowly began to form it would
take millions of years for Antarctica to
finally lock into a deep freeze and
during that time it remained warm enough
for plant life to survive evidence of
that was recently unearthed in a
relatively ice-free Valley in the
interior here geologist Alan Ashworth
and Adam Lewis find a remarkable fossil
oh wait is that a leaf there's a leaf
right there that leaf fell into the mud
maybe 20 million years ago suddenly do
the best is yet that's a sweet leaf and
then they find something extraordinary
this is like a peat peat moss and then
if we take T some of this out there
flight freeze-dried under the microscope
these brittle mosses are in pristine
condition
these moss fossils are not rock but
actual plant tissue the last vestiges of
vegetation from a time when Antarctica
was still warm
they were found under a layer of
volcanic ash that dates back millions of
years this is the original moss tissue
and even the cells are preserved in
these fossils these plants were
flash-frozen when an article plummeted
into a deep freeze that preserved them
until today it's mind-boggling the only
way is to say the climate remained very
very cold it remained very very dry and
it did not warm up for even relatively
short periods of time in this location
otherwise these things are gone
now as Earth is heating up what will
happen to Antarctica will it melt
raising sea levels all over the planet
how sensitive is this frozen land to the
temperature changes we currently face
but before researchers can investigate
in Antarctica last-minute testing is
taking place here over 2,000 miles away
in the countryside of New Zealand with a
brand new drill yeah it's a shakedown
we've got a few leaking connections and
things that don't quite fit as well as I
need to a little bit of modifications
required pretty common with a brand new
piece of equipment weighing in at a
whopping 40 tonnes this mechanized
marvel is as heavy as a humpback whale
and just as large towering some 5
stories high the giant rig will soon
dwarf everything in sight except the ice
this will be the largest Rorick in
Antarctica that's used on land and this
mammoth rig can drill in more than one
place that's because it's mounted on a
sled I think it probably is unusual all
of the equipment is on sledges so in
Antartica we pull it all with pygmy
bulldozers it's been specially designed
to drill from the ice in order to
extract hidden secrets from beneath
Antarctica itself
this unique multinational enterprise is
called an drill the Antarctic drilling
project for team leader David Harwood
it's a dream come true as a scientist
there's a passion there's a passion that
comes in trying to figure it out trying
to identify what has been the past
history of the ice sheet and wondering
what the future might hold
soon the giant drill will be dismantled
and ready for a long sea voyage this
will get you to take your extreme cold
weather days off but now the andrel team
gathers at Christchurch New Zealand for
the six-hour flight to Antarctica in a
c-17 cargo plane jam-packed with people
and gear their flight passes over the
Transantarctic mountains which divide
the continent into two regions with
colossal glaciers called ice sheets
blanketing both the giant East Antarctic
Ice Sheet is ten times the size of the
West it's frozen firmly to bedrock high
above the sea and in some places the ice
towers almost three miles into the sky
the smaller West Antarctic Ice Sheet is
less stable that's because it rests on
land well below sea level and it extends
hundreds of miles over the ocean in
floating ice shelves it's likely East
and West Antarctica will respond very
differently to a warming world
the andreal team touches down in the
West on an icy runway at McMurdo Station
the largest US research base in
Antarctica as David Harwood and Richard
levy step out onto the ice
the first thing they notice is the
weather is a bit chilly but it's
beautiful
it's October springtime and it's minus
20 degrees the earliest I've ever been
down to Antarctica and it's very cold
when the wind picks up it's rather an
unpleasant place to be working when the
wind isn't blowing and the sun shining
it's actually really quite nice but very
cold but even a sunny afternoon can turn
nasty in a moment's notice yes all day
McMurdo Station has been a vital hub of
research for over half a century what
began as a tiny outpost as over the
years grown into a small town
McMurdo houses a population of 200
people year round but during the
research season it becomes home base for
over a thousand every year McMurdo
supports scores of research projects
providing lab facilities food and
supplies and survival training for teams
of scientists who will head out to
remote field camps this season those
numbers include the andrel team of over
50 technicians and researchers from the
u.s. New Zealand Germany and Italy and
rule is funded by their governments and
the National Science Foundation there's
probably a week at least of work in
McMurdo where we have to get all of our
gear sorted out getting everything we
need in order to be able to work and
survive on the field as they gather
supplies for more than a month on the
ice one item is in high demand sugar
actually heats your body it gives you a
quick energy especially if you're like
freezing and we expect to be very cold
we don't really know how much chocolate
is enough we can take up to 560 candy
bars but I'm looking at this and I'm
already getting queasy I'm like oh I
don't know if I can eat this or not as
anvil researchers prepare for life in
the field they join hundreds of other
scientists fanning out across Antarctica
and many are focused on the same
question Kota Antarctica be headed for a
meltdown over here is Mount Boreas we're
gonna have a lot of scientists working
together there is a little bit of
volcanic ash and you know challenging
each other's theories challenging what
we know but if that as a community we're
gonna find the answers
you
but the continent won't give up its
secrets easily the stark beauty of
Antarctica masks a treacherous nature
more than seventy percent of all the
fresh water in the world is harbored
here but most of that water is frozen
and with less precipitation than the
Sahara Antarctica is the driest desert
on earth raging winds of up to 200 miles
per hour
sometimes blasts the frozen terrain
where temperatures can drop to a hundred
degrees below zero only during the short
Antarctic summer can most researchers
gather precious scientific data from
this giant mystery continent come to
light
that's all that and to me
for our flight and 400 miles for McMurdo
is the center of the West Antarctic Ice
Sheet and for one team this is the best
way to find out about the past this is a
side of a snow pit it's a thin wall
between two pits the other side is open
so they can light can shine through and
you can really see the different layers
in the pit so this is one year's worth
of snow accumulation and there's a
second year's worth of snow accumulation
here below it two years of record right
here in the snow pit of course we want
to go back a lot further in time than
that in order to do that we can't just
use shovels and chainsaws like we did
here
so we have to use a drill
ken Taylor's team is drilling through
ice their goal is to gather samples from
the nearly two mile thick West Antarctic
Ice Sheet and the deeper they go the
further back in time they travel here at
about 480 meters deep right now this is
right around the time when Jesus lived
it's right about zero ad right when BC
years turned into 80 years these ice
cores contain tiny bubbles of ancient
atmosphere that were trapped each year
as the snow was compressed into ice nice
bubbles in this one it's ancient area
there when we crush samples like this I
don't get the cows out there and we can
sample the ancient atmosphere
we can also get a record of how things
like temperature and sea ice changed in
the past by combining these different
records we can understand how the
climate system is operating the past
but the ice work valuable as it is only
goes back about eight hundred thousand
years a tiny fraction of geologic time
to get a more complete picture of
Antarctica's climate history you have to
drill farther back in time and that's
what the andreal team is trying to do
they want to paint a picture of
Antarctica as it changed from warm to
cold millions of years ago in order to
do that
andr will have to drill deep into the
earth but finding the right location is
a major challenge on a continent covered
by ice and even in those few places
where the ice has receded it's still not
easy and rills David Harwood and Richard
levy are searching for places to drill
but as they fly over a field of rubble
they see the gathering evidence for a
chronological history is not possible
here something has stirred things up and
that something is the ice itself that's
because ice moves for tens of millions
of years glaciers have slowly scoured
the land gobbling up rocks and debris
and spreading them all across the
landscape in random order this we call
glacial paleontology some call it
garbage pile paleontology because we're
looking and sorting through these
Marines to try to get pieces of
information that the ice sheet has
brought to us a marine is the chaotic
accumulation of rocks and debris
deposited by glacial movement this one
here she has abundant shell fossils this
shell brought here by a glacier comes
from a time when the continent was
warmer and water ran through these
valleys this landscape is a treasure
trove of a Nordica's climate history but
the ice has scrambled all the clues
we're looking at a jigsaw puzzle yet
there's one place where the evidence
remains intact that's in the seafloor
beneath the Antarctic ice shelf where
the glacial movement has also deposited
layer after layer in chronological order
drilling gives us an opportunity to get
a serial history in time each layer goes
back in time and we know that a rock
was younger than a rock below so we
could put it into history the andrel
team aims to drill through the Antarctic
ice and the sea below then like a straw
thrust through a layer cake they'll bore
deep into the ocean floor in order to
recover millions of years of rock and
mud the trace Antarctica's climate
history even after ice began to form in
Antarctica around 34 million years ago
the continent remained warm enough for
plant life to survive a lot like areas
of New Zealand today where ice can be
found bordered by trees and plants but
when did Antarctica plunge into a solid
deep freeze and how did it happen
was it gradual or abrupt
will the story of how Antarctica changed
from green house to ice house reveal new
clues about the continents climate
future and our own Charlie I am David
Harwood
the andrel team will spend the next few
weeks searching for drilling locations
from the surface of the ice but David
Harwood remains focused on what lies
below when I'm driving across there I'm
always thinking about what's beneath
this I'm over about 15 feet of ice and
over that I'm over about 1,500 feet of
water and then the sediments below that
here at the bottom of the world the Sun
never sets in the summer and his night
blends in today the work begins in
earnest the team heads out to McMurdo
Sound a place where the ocean freezes
annually creating a precarious platform
of floating sea ice that will only last
a few months we're standing right now in
the southern part of the proto Sound
seasonally this region will break out
the sea ice that are standing on the
melt out it's now strong enough perhaps
20 feet beneath us is a thickness of ice
and then 15 hundred feet of water
beneath us as well just to be sure
they're in the right place fire in the
hole the team blasts powerful sound
waves through the sea ice
and into the sea floor below the result
is a sonic street map of layer after
layer of rock and mud each one
representing a different era of the past
by looking in the past we can may be
projecting to the future how dynamic has
been the behavior of the ice sheets have
they been static
and slowly changing act of a player have
they been
finally it's time to tow the giant drill
out onto the ice to ensure that the
weight of the rig isn't supported by the
sea ice alone
divers attach flotation devices to the
drill pipe and at the end of that pipe
is a whirling tool with a unique cutting
edge a drill bit made of diamonds that
can bore through almost everything in
its pad the diamond core system that we
have it's almost like melting the core
down through the rocks just cuts through
whatever's there if you hit a big
boulder you'll just end up with a
cylinder of that Boulder but it just
keep going now the real drilling begins
there's not a minute to waste because
the Antarctic research season is so
short
the crews work around the clock
to recover cores of rock the trace
Antarctica's ancient past
the powerful drill bores down over
three-quarters of a mile
bringing up 12 feet of core at a time
each foot averaging a thousand years of
climate history
it's an astonishing feat it's quite
amazing when you think about where we
are and what we're doing we've got a
drill rig a 60 ton 290 ton with all the
equipment on a drill rig sitting behind
us here on eight meters of sea ice above
380 meters of water and then we're
drilling down into the sea floor below
there with a three to four inch diameter
pipe that's turning round and round like
a a piece of spaghetti hanging down
through the water and into the ground
and it's wobbling around a bit and we're
turning around and bringing Cora from
deep within the earth anything can go
wrong at any minute with this process
and all too soon it does sometimes even
a drill bit made of diamonds can run
into trouble we haven't been getting
particularly good quality core and we're
suspecting that the drill bit has been
damaged in places it's a little bit
narrower it should be for the size of
the diamond bits and that means we have
to pull our pipe out about 1700 meters
and replace a bit
right back down the hole and that's
going to take us about 24 hours to 36
hours removing and replacing nearly a
mile of pipe is no easy task especially
when it's your job to change it all out
piece by piece but for other members of
the andrel team it's a welcome break in
an extreme environment like Antarctica
nobody's on a diet your body is working
so hard to stay warm packing away 6,000
calories or more a day is not an
indulgence it's a necessity
and because Antarctica is drier than the
hottest desert dehydration is a constant
concern and keeping the drill up and
running is another
finally after a day and a half of hard
work the new bid is in place and
drilling is back on track they recover a
12-foot length of core wrapped in a
protective cover workers carefully carry
it back to the lab to be examined when
they crack it open it's in perfect
condition this mud and rock is more
valuable than gold because each core is
a time machine we're currently down to
the depth of body 440 meters that's
about a quarter mile down corresponding
to a time at least 15 million years ago
when Antarctica was still warm as the
cores are recovered each section is
sliced lengthwise x-rayed and scanned in
labs at the drill site and back at
McMurdo this course came out of the
ground three days ago they were split
yesterday they were imaged yesterday
sedimentology stew worked the night
shift 12 hours describing these pours
millimeter by millimeter looking at the
color size ratios any kind of structure
they see in a core trying to understand
how these sediments were deposited each
core tells a story depending on its
texture color and contents and some of
those stories are spectacular we're
seeing some macro fossils some large
shells these shells are evidence of
warmer times even as Antarctica is icing
up this is one the most particular
fossil found within and really decision
this is a scallop now this kind of
scalloped simply do not live in extreme
polar waters
and there are other clues
some of them nearly invisible hidden
inside these cores are shells of
microscopic algae called diatoms for
Andrew climate detectives these tiny
diatoms create a highly revealing
picture of the past because not all
diatoms are alike some species are
adapted to colder conditions while
others flourish in warmer waters we use
them as biological markers index of
different environmental conditions cold
or warm frozen waters or open ocean
waters again the andrel team examines
cores from around 15 million years ago
they find smooth green sands containing
diatoms that thrived in relatively warm
water confirming this was a time before
antarctica finally froze over this is
very well-defined warm period iceberg
free waters open waters where diatoms
are growing and thriving you can see
this persistent for quite some time a
picture is beginning to form of a long
period of transition starting 34 million
years ago when a cooling climate led to
the formation of ice but even so
conditions remained relatively mild but
when did Antarctica finally slip into a
deep freeze the answer lies in cores
from around 14 million years ago
instead of smooth and green these cores
are rocky and gray and some contain
diatoms that thrived in cold glacial
waters this amazing discovery reveals a
rapid change from cool to frozen it
fills in what has always been a blank
page in Antarctica's climate history
next season they'll attack another
crucial question after Antarctica froze
14 million years ago did the ice ever
melt or has it remained a frozen
wilderness right up until today that
answer will have to wait
cracks in the sea-ice tell the team it's
time to return to base we've seen the
ice break in quite a bit in the last
month but it's not broken in anywhere
anywhere further south than it is right
now we can only be on this site for so
long before the sea ice starts to melt
before the conditions change and for
safety reasons we have to get off the
sea ice the precarious sea ice of West
Antarctica may come and go with the
seasons but what about the giant East
Antarctic Ice Sheet a mountain of ice so
high it covers mountains this is like an
MRI of the ice sheet some places it's
really thick two miles thick and pretty
flat and boring but then there are other
places where what we discovered were
hidden mountain ranges the size of the
Appalachians but totally hidden by the
huge you said Artic ice sheet there's
ten times as much ice in the east as in
the west but a small portion of the East
has almost no ice at all
it's an unearthly location that defies
the very image of Antarctica
these are the Dry Valleys cold barren
and except for a few scientists almost
completely devoid of life the landscape
is so alien nASA has used it as a test
site for space programs it's a fantastic
place you can't find this anywhere else
on earth
it's closest analogue is the surface of
Mars Mullins Valley is the ultimate
remote field camp it serves as home base
for a pioneering band of glaciologists
led by Dave Marchand
Marsh aunt and his team are conducting
research the rugged old-fashioned way
they'll live in tents and won't be
picked up for two months they need to be
self-sufficient and for the most part
they like it that way good day
burritos the good thing about working
out here is it's actually double-edged
sword you come out here you have no
contact with the outside world no email
no real telephone contacts so you can
totally immerse yourself in the science
and that allows you to think 24 hours a
day about what you're doing the other
side of that is you have no idea what's
going on outside right beginning of the
season I didn't like it when there you
would breathe and the frost would form
on the outside of the sleeping bag but
it hold up now and it's a little more
comfortable and a lot easier small
setups like we have which are helicopter
supported are isolated they're among the
most isolated in the region and as a
result we have to check in daily with
McMurdo I'll try to heat the batteries
up so that we can get a signal out right
now there appears to be no satellite
coverage and the batter is a little bit
cold so I'm trying to warm it up
sometimes you have to contort your body
in various ways to get the signal no not
we don't have enough signal yet well
here we go we've got something that
might work
Mac ops this is gone for Mullins Valley
we have seven on board and all as well
over are we lost transmission
this valley holds an incredible record
this area is so dry and so cold that the
landscape is pristine the rocks we see
here are millions of years old more
shock believes that little has changed
here for millions of years what to me is
exciting is that we're walking on an
ancient landscape imagine living ten
million years ago in Antarctica this is
what you'd see exactly as it is today
hardly modified at all
but when marshawn's team drilled beneath
this rubble they found something totally
unexpected
a hidden glacier that extends hundreds
of feet below the surface this is in my
opinion the oldest dated berry glacier
on earth the evidence comes from
volcanic ash the dry valleys are
surrounded by extinct volcanoes that
erupted millions of years ago we're
finding ash deposits on top of ice ash
dates are coming back as old as 8
million years and according to more shot
this volcanic ash shows this hidden
glacier once frozen has never melted
this volcanic ash that erupted from a
volcano and has been sitting there for
millions of years it shows no chemical
alteration which you'd expect if there
were any amount of liquid meltwater over
that duration the fact that it's dry and
pristine tells me it's always been here
which is incredible equally astonishing
and just three hundred miles away there
appears to be a completely different
picture exploring East Antarctica closer
to the South Pole and riyals David
Harwood found leaf fossils and pieces of
wood surprisingly according to Harwood
these date to a relatively recent time
when Antarctica was not only warmer than
today there were plants and trees this
is a piece of southern beach this wood
is not fossilized in the sense that it
is petrified it could still burn to find
the wood and leaves together
it is pretty phenomenal it's really
phenomenal for Antarctica particularly
for Antarctica in the in this time
period about 4 million years ago
this season the drill is setup to find
evidence of what happened in Antarctica
during this period three to five million
years ago it's a time known as the
Pliocene now what's important about that
is that the Pliocene was globally warmer
than today the same temperatures as our
earth may be headed for at the end of
the century if climate change
predictions are correct if we go back
three to five million years into the
geological past we know that there was a
time when Earth's climate was warmer
than it is today
perhaps by 3 to 4 degrees so it's the
best example we have of where the
climate is heading in the next hundred
years
the drills new location is on the giant
Ross Ice Shelf which extends out and
over the ocean
it's the largest ice shelf in the world
and it helps hold back the massive
Antarctic Ice Sheet
from flowing into the sea these ice
shelves are very important what they do
is hold back the flow of ice that's
actually trying to flow out into the
ocean we call that buttressing if
warming oceans cause the Ross Ice Shelf
to break up and melt into the sea the
West Antarctic Ice Sheet would
eventually follow right behind
the andrel team is looking for the
answer to a critical question when Earth
was warming during the Pliocene what
happened to the ice did the Ross Ice
Shelf melt taking the giant ice sheets
with it drilling on an ice shelf brings
with it a unique set of technological
challenges
including constant problems with mud and
water
unlike drilling through sea ice which is
just 26 feet thick the ice shelf here is
400 feet we're looking at at least
doubling or trying to double our
capability below the sea floor and
penetrate 2,000 meters or better into
the sea floor but that's only the
beginning no one has ever drilled
through an ice shelf and they present
these challenges the ice shelves they
float up and down with the tide so
you've got to deal with this vertical
elevation change they move sideways they
flow so eventually your drill pipe is
going to get bent can the drill bore
through a thick layer of ice that's
constantly moving without breaking or
getting yanked out of the sea floor to
confront this unique challenge head-on
the Android team invents a new tool a
hot-water drill this marvel of
engineering is a moving ring of heat
that blasts jets of steaming water to
melt a wide hole so the drill can
operate freely through four hundred feet
of shifting ice and once again time is
so precious the team must work around
the clock not only retrieving cores but
also analyzing them it's 2:00 a.m. but
you wouldn't know it geologists are busy
logging cores like it's early afternoon
we're laying out the cores and a proper
sequence from top grade highest point in
the core all the way to the very slowest
point of the quarter an 80-foot core
that dates back about three million
years is closely examined it contains
micro fossils of single-celled animals
known as forums
they're from the crucial warm period
called the Pliocene and these tiny
shells are precise indicators of ocean
temperature these guys are about the
size of a grain of sand because the same
species lived through time we can use
the chemistry of modern examples to
allow us to calibrate if you like the
chemistry of the ancient examples what
Gabe's doing here is he's measuring the
amount of two metals magnesium and
calcium that are in the ocean and get
incorporated into the shell of the 4m
when it's growing in that ocean and that
process is dependent on the temperature
of the ocean so if we know the magnesium
we know the calcium we can determine the
temperature of the ocean at the time
that forum lived and because of that
Andrew researchers can now calculate
Antarctic water temperatures during the
Pliocene what this is telling us as
temperatures were three to four perhaps
five degrees above prison
even just one degree rise notion
temperatures in the waters surrounding
Antarctica will attack and begin to melt
the ice shelves from below
very quickly the air temperatures will
stay cold enough to keep things frozen
at the surface but what we're worried
about is the ice being attacked from
beneath not from above and the cores
revealed that this is what happened
during the Pliocene when global climate
was warming but they display even more
change than expected revealing not only
a patchwork of glacial rubble but also
smooth mud from open seas indicating
that ice both froze and then melted many
times there's a really important change
right here this involves us quite a
dramatic change in the environment there
was ice and then there was no ice the
ice shade has gone backwards and
forwards it's advanced and it's
retreated as they examine core after
core from the Pliocene they continue to
see surprising signs of change the
results of the drilling are simply
spectacular they give us a picture of a
dynamic ice sheet coming and going
regularly more than 60 times what we're
seeing and this record is telling us
that Antarctica's not just a benign
spectator
it's a playa what this means is while it
was generally warm during the Pliocene
there were also brief periods of cooling
and the ice was exquisitely sensitive to
even small changes in climate just a few
degrees could tip the scale from ice to
no ice so what's in store for our future
as Earth continues to warm how much
Antarctic ice will melt and how high
will sea levels rise and rule scientists
turned to computer models by Rob de
canto and Dave Pollard we developed
these climate models based on our best
understanding of the physics of the
climate system and in this case ice
sheets and now information from anvil is
added to the climate model this is a
computer model simulation of the
Antarctic Ice Sheet over the last
several million years and covers a good
chunk of the interval that was recovered
by the andrel sediment core so we're
looking for the same kind of behavior in
our models that we're seeing in the
geological record as the model simulates
the warming periods of the Pliocene all
of the ice shelves disappear followed by
the entire West Antarctic Ice Sheet and
edges of the east and as temperatures
change the ice refreezes and melts again
and again and that's important because
the changes in the ice sheet that we're
seeing here reflect pretty significant
changes in sea level
according to the cantos model sea levels
rose about 23 feet during the Pliocene
temperatures back then were three to
five degrees higher than now just what's
projected to take place
by the end of the century but there is a
lag time in the way ice responds that
may delay the impact for hundreds if not
thousands of years
regardless coastal cities all over the
world would be at risk potentially
displacing millions we would be
remapping places like Boston in New York
the Bay Area not to mention of course
places like Louisiana Miami New Orleans
of course but even that might not be the
worst-case scenario
things were very similar to today in
terms of our climate
Tim Nations robbed a Kanto to New
Zealand to look at a possibility that's
even more frightening this is the first
time I've seen the actual direct
evidence for what the models are doing
you seeing a deepening syllable rise up
through here we're going to look at some
rocks set at the same age as rocks look
drilled and Antarctica that give us the
record of global sea level changes here
along the ranga tiki river tectonic
forces have raised the land and the
river has cut into the earth to expose
layer after layer of sediment that once
was the sea floor what they find our
shells dated to the warming era of the
Pliocene these shells provide a way to
chart sea level in the past because some
of these species still exist today many
of these Shoals you see in here actually
live today so they live around the
coastline and we know the water depth
they live in today so by breaking them
out of these rocks and identifying them
we can say the depth they were living
here over three million years ago
because these shellfish live on the
seafloor and can only survive in water
at specific depths they suggest that sea
levels in the Pliocene were much higher
than even the computer models predict
this is really a troll
this is where we would say we had the
evidence for sea level being up to as
much as 20 meters about Britain that's
over 60 feet in order for sea level to
arisen that high an enormous amount of
ice must have melted and this raises a
startling possibility that a large part
of the vast East Antarctic Ice Sheet
melted along with the West and if it
melted once could it melt again that
could be a very bad thing because that
would actually produce a contribution to
future sea level change that we really
haven't been thinking about this
presents an even more dangerous and
unpredictable picture of Antarctica
what's been surprising is even
geologists thought that glaciers and ice
sheets were these large static features
which we would never really see change
in our lifetime but glacial processes
are no longer quite as glacial things
are moving faster than we had thought
what's driving these changes are rising
levels of greenhouse gases in the next
five years greenhouse gas levels will be
like they were in the Pliocene but we're
not just going back to the Pliocene some
of the projections put co2 levels at
twice the concentrations of the Pliocene
by the end of the next century we're
essentially going back to the time of
the dinosaurs when there was very little
ice on the planet and there were forests
covering Antarctica and signs of change
are already here scientists were
completely caught by surprise when in
2002 the Larsen Ice Shelf shattered
apart without warning in just a few
weeks and today the Wilkins Ice Shelf a
block of ice approximately the size of
Connecticut barely hangs on I would say
it's inevitable that Western occur will
disappear how long it will take you
start occur to engage is something
that's that's not yet known in the
coming years the Andhra team will
continue to explore Antarctica's climate
history in order to gain valuable
insight into Earth's future with each
new core we gain new knowledge about a
continent that's always been shrouded in
mystery but it's faith remains very much
tied to our own
this nova program is available on DVD at
Shaw PBS org or call 1-800 play PBS
you