this is the briefing, i'm sally bundock.
our top story: thousands of iranians spend
a second night without shelter after sunday's
devastating earthquake.
the search for survivors continues.
anti-trump protestors clash with police in
the philippine capital, manila, on the last
day of the us president's tour of asia. and
the largest diamond ever put up for auction.
it could be yours forjust $30 million.
the art of the deal.
trump's team says the us has struck $300 billion
worth of trade and investment deals during
his asian trip.
we investigate.
in business briefing, i will be talking to
an international business guru to find out
the real benefit to business from trump's
trip.
a warm welcome to the programme,
briefing you on all you need to know in global
news, business, and sport. and it is a debate
about the king of sports that is raging on
social media, after italy failed to qualify
for the world cup for the first time in 60
years.
la gazzetta dello sport is asking, what should
italian football fans do now in june 2018?
send in your ideas.
just use the hashtag #bbcthebriefing.
thousands of survivors of a powerful earthquake
that struck the mountainous border region
between iran and iraq have spent a second
night without shelter.
the country is observing a day of national
mourning for the more than 400 people who
were killed
when the 7.3-magnitude quake struck near the
iran-iraq border, just under 30km south of
the city of halabja.
sarah corker reports.
this is the deadliest earthquake in the world
this year.
the border town here in western iran bore
the brunt of it.
homes were flattened in seconds, crushing
everyone inside.
the search for survivors has been frantic,
early this morning, iranian officials called
off the rescue operation.
at this local hospital, many of the injured
had stories of narrow escapes.
translation: i fell from the balcony down.
the earthquake was very strong.
translation: the earthquake shattered the
window, which fell on me, and it wounded my
hand and my face.
this mountainous area is prone to earthquakes.
power cuts and landslides have made it difficult
for rescue teams to get in.
the most severely hurt have been airlifted
out, some taken to hospital in the iranian
capital, tehran.
but, overwhelmed by the sheer number of injured,
the authorities are appealing for people to
donate blood.
and this is the moment this 7.3 magnitude
quake hit in neighbouring iraq. a man runs
for his life from the control room of this
dam. boulders were tossed around like pebbles,
and with cracks appearing in the structure,
there are now concerns about the safety of
the dam. translation: when the quake started,
rocks from the mountains started, rocks from
the mountains started falling on the street,
and damaged cars.
it even cause damage
to the walls of the dam. a picture of widespread
devastation is emerging.
hundreds dead, thousands injured, many missing.
turkey has sent a convoy of aid trucks, medication,
10th and blankets, and many have spent a second
night outdoors, terrified by the after-shocks.
so far there have been more than 190 of them
-- tents. and we have more detail on that
story on our website, and we will discuss
it later in the programme.
theresa may has launched her strongest attack
yet on russia.
speaking at the lord mayor's banquet in london,
the british prime minister said russia must
choose a very different path from the one
that had seen moscow annex crimea, foment
conflict in ukraine, and launch cyber attacks
on governments and parliaments across europe.
russia has fomented conflict in the donbass,
repeatedly violated
the national airspace of several european
countries, and mounted a sustained campaign
of cyber espionage and disruption.
this has included meddling in elections, and
hacking the danish ministry of defence and
the bundestag, among many others.
it is seeking to weaponise information, deploying
its state-run media organisations to plant
fake stories and photoshopped images, in an
attempt to sow discord in the west and undermine
our institutions.
so i have a very simple message for russia.
we know what you are doing, and you will not
succeed.
because you underestimate the resilience of
our democracies, the enduring attraction of
free and open societies, and the commitment
of western nations to the alliances that bind
us.
protesters have marched
towards the presidential palace in manila,
as leaders gathered for the second day of
the asean summit.
it is the final day of president trump's mammoth
tour of asian countries.
it began 11 days ago with him touching down
in japan, and before the day is out, he will
be back in washington, dc. howard johnsonjoins
us from the philippines’ capital, manila.
howard, it is quite a big day, as president
trump heads back to the united states.
what is on the agenda, what will dominate
today?
well, what dominates today happens in about
half an hour in a building behind me.
it is the east asia summit, it is the showpiece
of the 50th anniversary asean summit that
we are attending here.
what it is is it isa we are attending here.
what it is is it is a grouping of regional
leaders who will be discussing with dialogue
partners like the united states and
japan, they will talk about issues about regional
security here.
so donald trump will be there to hear concerns
about islamic state in southeast asia. he
will also hear about north korea's missile
threats.
but the biggest issue that always comes up
at these summits is the south china sea, so
they will be talking about how can they come
together to agree a code of conduct that can
decide how they manage these waterways? we
can see trillions of dollars worth of trade
passed through these waters every year, and
america is keen to reassert its influence
in this area, as china builds up sandbags
and islands over the last year while the leaders
in this region have tried to work out this
code of conduct.
quite interesting, on that issue with the
philippines, being a bit softer towards china,
it would seem, this time around, under president
duterte.
yes, what we have seen is, in the previous
administration,
there was an effort to try to reassert filipino
influence in this story.
what they did was they took this case to the
international arbitration court, and they
won this case, saying that china could not
lay claim to that area.
since president duterte came to power, he
hasn't really acted on this, and he hasn't
really acted on this, and he has tried to
really curry favour with china. he has been
softer on the approach, and his foreign minister
even said that they won't really looking for
a legally binding code of conduct this afternoon,
but rather a gentleman's agreement, that they
could all somehow muddle through this without
a legal document to really attack it down.
0k, document to really attack it down.
ok, for now, howard johnson in manila, thank
you.
let's brief you on some of the other stories
making the news: there have been further calls
by us republicans for the party's alabama
senate candidate, roy moore, to stand down,
following a wave of allegations of sexual
misconduct by him against teenage girls decades
ago.
a fifth woman has come forward and said he
groped her when she was 16.
mr moore has denied all the accusations against
him.
protesters have interrupted a pro-fossil fuel
presentation by white house advisers by breaking
into song.
the us officials were promoting wider use
of fossilfuels on the sidelines of a un climate
conference in germany.
they say what is known as clean coal must
be part of the solution to global warming.
international creditors holding $60 million
of creditors' -- $60 billion of them is whether’s
bonds have said
no deal has been made.
their economic situation is blamed on economic
situation is blamed on economic sabotage by
the united states.
the white house is touting the rather whopping
figure of $300 billion in deals during the
president's swing through asia. the lion's
share of that, $250 billion, came during his
trip to china.
liam booth-smith, chief executive of localis,
an independent think tank, joins me now.
i will be speaking to you a little later in
the news briefing.
but first, let's talk about donald trump's
asia trip, and the deals he struck while there.
when you dig a bit deeper, it is not quite
as cut and dry as that, is it? know, and president
trump drawing a long line in recent history
of leaders who have gone to china and come
back, trumping, as it were, their economic
success and the deals they have signed.
what is
interesting about this is that rex tillerson
has said, and i quote, the deals are pretty
small.
a lot of it is stuff that is always the being
announced, some of it is deals where there
is no firm commitment, just a promise -- already
being announced.
it is very much in line with the trump economic
policy, and there is also a deal where china
will now have access to the us domestic energy
supply.
general electric, is that the one with general
electric?
that's quite true, yes.
it is interesting, isn't it? because there
has been an opening up of the market in both
directions, it seems, which is helpful to
the united states and china.
what about other countries? we are still to
hear from the philippines if anything was
struck that, but deals have been done with
japan, south korea, for example.
still relatively small.
what has happened in the summit at the moment
is that deals for the us outside of
china appeared to be relatively small, and
the discussions from trump, what has come
out of his camp, seems to be largely about
security.
and that contrasts very interestingly with
the very hard economic position they are taking
with china.
thank you very much indeed.
liam is going to get a strong coffee, he is
looking at some of the other stories today.
join our conversation regarding the football
world cup.
italy did not qualify, so we are asking along
with the italian press what italian fans should
be doing injune next year.
so far, many of your comments i cannot say
on the television.
0ne viewer says enjoy the world cup with no
tension.
that is her advice.
stay with us on the briefing. also on the
programme: italy fails to qualify for the
world cup, for the first time in 60 years.
that and more in the sport briefing.
berliners from both east and west linked hands
and danced
round their liberated territory.
and, with nobody to stop them, it wasn't long
before the first attempts were made to destroy
the structure itself.
it's keeping the candidate's name always in
the public eye that counts.
success or failure depends not only on public
display but on the local campaign headquarters
and the heavy routine work of their women
volunteers.
yasser arafat, who dominated the palestinian
cause for so long, has died.
the palestinian authority has declared a state
of mourning for the leader who symbolised
his people's hopes for independent statehood.
in the wake of the colombian volcano disaster,
rescue teams are trying to reach thousands
of survivors who managed to clamber onto rooftops
and trees above the sea of mud. after 17 years
of discussion, the result was greeted with
an outburst ofjoy.
women ministers who'd long felt only grudgingly
accepted amongst the ranks of clergy suddenly
felt welcomed.
you're watching the briefing.
0ur headlines: thousands of iranians have
spent a second night without shelter - after
sunday's devastating earthquake.
tehran has declared a national day of mourning.
anti-trump protestors have clashed with police
in the philippine capital manila - on the
last day of the us president's tour of asia.
here's our briefing on some of the key events
happening later.
let's start off with a bang in california,
where nasa will launch a cutting-edge environmental
satellite at 9.117 on the dot, gmt time.
the shoebox size machine will provide advanced
tracking of weather events during its 10-year
orbit.
later on in london, a brexit milestone will
be made when mps debate the eu withdrawal
bill as it begins its committee stage in the
commons.
the talks also mark exactly 500 days before
the uk's scheduled departure
from the eu. and in the afternoon, attorney
generaljeff sessions testifies before the
housejudiciary committee in washington.
he's likely to be pressed over his "inconsistencies"
on the trump campaign's russia connections.
in the uk, members of parliament will today
begin debating a key piece of brexit legislation,
it the eu withdraw bill.
that will turn european laws into uk ones
opponents including rebels from the ruling
conservative party have tabled scores of amendments.
0ur correspondent reports.
is still the one in charge, theresa may last
night at the glittering
lord mayor ‘s banquet in london.
a breakfrom lord mayor ‘s banquet in london.
a break from wrecks it and potential trouble
ahead.
a key piece of the government's brexit legislation
returns to the commons today.
and mps are trying to tinker with there.
they are proposing hundreds of changes to
try to influence the approach of ministers.
and so yesterday, an apparent concession to
one of their key demands.
yesterday, an apparent concession to one of
their key demandslj yesterday, an apparent
concession to one of their key demands.
i can now confirm that once we have reached
an agreement, we will bring forward a specific
piece of legislation to implement the agreement.
parliament will be given time to debate, suit
grew tonight and vote on this final at deal.
it will only hold if parliament approves it.
but was such a fragile majority, only a handful
of tory backbenchers siding with the opposition
would lead to a defeat for the government.
and those in mind to rebel seem unsatisfied
with the take it or leave it vote the government
has offered.
the take it or leave it vote the government
has offeredlj the take it or leave it vote
the government has offered.
i must say, many of us insulted by this.
they
sounded so good and then when you dug into
the detail you realise that this is meaningful
vote was meaning less.
there will be more contentious votes here
in the coming weeks as mps votes here in the
coming weeks as m ps test votes here in the
coming weeks as mps test the government's
fragile working majority.
now with news about italy's failure to reach
next year's world cup finals and the rest
of today's sport briefing here's tulsen tollett.
hello i'm tulsen tollett - here's what's coming
up in your sport briefing this tuesday.
it's crunch time for denmark and the republic
of ireland as they bid to book their place
in russia 2018.
but there's no place for italy after losing
out to swden in their play-off, while roger
federer continues his bid to win a seventh
atp tour finals title there are nowjust three
spots left at the russia world cup next year.
one of those will go to either the republic
of ireland or denmark later on tuesday night.
the second leg of their playoff is in dublin,
with honours even after a goalless draw in
copenhagen.
denmark had the better of the chances in the
first leg, while ireland were criticised for
a lack of creativity.
you have to try and cover all eventualities
but it only takes a second to score a goal,
so the minute a goal is scored in the game,
that eradicates a lot of things, it eradicates
extra time, it eradicates penalty kicks and
things like that we may need a couple of goals
to keep out denmark for two games might be
tough.
there are a number of international friendlies
around the world on tuesday. one of those
is england against brazil.
brazil were the first team to qualify for
the russia world cup way back in march.
with the likes of neymar and coutinho in their
squad, england boss gareth southgate says
they're "the best team in the world", but
he won't be afraid of picking a young team
to face them.
now, in case you missed it, italy won't be
playing at next
year's world cup in russia. it's the first
time since 1958 the azzurri have missed out
on the sports showpiece event after losing
out on aggregate to sweden in their two legged
qualifier.
the second leg in milan finished goalless
despite the best efforts of the hosts to manufacture
a goal meaning the 1-0 win for the swedes
in stockholm last week proved the difference
while the italian manager gian piero ventura
who has only been in charge for 17 months
will now come under serious presssure.
rafael nadal is out of the season-ending atp
world tour finals.
the spaniard withdrew with a knee injury after
losing his opening match to belgium's david
goffin in a tough three set match that took
more than two and a half hours to complete
against the 26-year-old, meaning nadal’s
fellow spaniard pablo carreno busta comes
in as the alternate for the next two matches.
now, cyclist chris froome has won the tour
de france four times but he's still hungry
for more! at 32 the british rider says he's
still excited by the prospect of racing and
he's hungry
for a fifth tour title.
it's a good question.
i definitely don't feel as if i'm there yet.
i guess i'll know when the time is right.
but for the time being i'm still hungry, still
motivated to keep trying to win another tour
de france and i'm just going to take it one
year at a time.
so long as the body's able to do this then
i'm going to keep going.
four-time champions italy failed to reach
the world cup for the first time since 1958
after a play-off defeat against sweden.
there's been plenty of reaction on social
media.
the gazetta dello sport doesn't mince its
words.
this was their headline not long after the
match finished, saying that it's an apocalypse.
zlatan ibrahimovic, the former sweden international
and now manchester united player recovering
from injury posted a picture of the team saying
"we are zweden" while the official italy twitter
account tweeted a quote from gigi buffon saying
"blame is shared equallly
between everyone.
there can't be scapegoats.
win together, lose together.
you can get all the latest sports news at
our website - that's bbc.com/sport.
but for now from me, tulsen tollett, that's
your sport briefing.
many of you have not been so diplomatic when
it comes to the outcome of the game with italy.
basically we have a lot of advice for italian
football fans about what they should do injune
of next year.
peter yates from england suggest that they
support england instead.
a woman from vancouver suggests pastor.
-- pasta. and a man from australia suggest
that they practise football and not diving.
there's more than a little sparkle brightening
up the november gloom in geneva this week.
some of the world's rarest and most valuable
gemstones are up for auction, they all command
multi million dollar price tags, but there
is one particular diamond which is attracting
special attention - and it goes under the
hammer tonight.
imogen foulkes has been along to have a look.
there is more than a little sparkle in geneva
this dull november.
every year the jewellery houses compete to
show that one special stone the rarest, the
purest, the most vivid.
but this year there is one extraordinary showstopper.
that is 163 carats. this is the largest diamond
ever to be put up for auction.
to show it at its best, or maybe to make sure
potential buyers don't mistake it for an ice
cube, it has been set into a string of emeralds.
59119 of them.
add to that,
862 diamonds on the other side and this piece
makes all sorts of records.
but there is one especially important number
everybody wants to know.
how much? we expect to in the region of $30
million for it.
it is the largest flawless diamond ever to
come to market.
finest colour, finest clarity and extraordinary
proportions.
there is a temptation with a diamond crystal
to cut the largest possible and end up with
a stone that is possibly lopsided or lumpy,
just to keep the weight.
not here.
this is perfection.
the diamond is brand-new.
0nly mind last year.
but history is going under the hammer in geneva
as well.
this 19 ca rat hammer in geneva as well.
this 19 carat diamond graced the grounds of
french kings for 350 years.
pink.
yellow.
necklace, ring or brooch,
jewellery lovers are spoilt for choice.
but while many will look, with his multi-
million-dollar pricetag is, only a few will
be able to purchase.
stay with me on bbc news, i'll be back with
the business briefing in just a few moments
- we'll have more on the deals struck by president
trump during his asia trip.
we will have the other business stories as
well.
you can always refer to the bbc news app,
co nsta ntly refer to the bbc news app, constantly
updating about that story in iraq and iran.
in the next an hour here on bbc news i will
be speaking to our correspondent who is in
the nearest town to the epicentre in iraq
where this happened.
we have
been hearing from people on the ground throughout
this story in the last few days since the
earthquake struck on sunday. also there are
many other stories on the bbc global page,
on our news app. take a look at when you have
time.
also as well we are asking you today what
do you think italian football fans should
be doing injune 2018 after that terrible news
for them last night.
the italy did not qualify for the world cup
next year in russia.
many of you had sent in your thoughts and
ideas.
many have been suggesting that they just enjoy
the world cup for a change without all the
stress.
there is a thought.
i will see you inafew there is a thought.
i will see you in a few minutes.
hi there.
yesterday was a pretty chilly day, with temperatures
between five and seven celsius.
it was even cold enough for a bit of snow
in scotland.
i know many of us go nuts for snow, but these
scenes are likely to be short-lived, because
the air is going to be turning a little bit
milder today.
the cold weather we had yesterday was due
to these northerly winds moving down across
the uk. but we've had a change of wind direction
over the last 12 hours orso, dragging in much
milder conditions.
a weak weather front lying across central
portions of the uk will thicken the cloud
up, to bring us some spots of light rain or
drizzle.
so today it will be cloudy and it will also
be a mild today as the wind changes direction.
here is the forecast.
first thing in the morning, these are the
temperatures if you step outside early.
patches of rain around in northern scotland
where it may also be cold enough for pockets
of frost. for england and wales, a cloud to
start the day really temperatures will range
from
7- 12 really temperatures will range from
7- 12 degrees.
the cloud will bring is patches of rain across
wales.
parts of the midlands, east anglia and north-west
england also looked down.
it will be cloudy in northern ireland but
in scotland the weather is quite different.
a few showers in the far north but otherwise
a fine and crisp, sunny start to the day.
a bit of frost perhaps across the sheltered
northern areas.
in the rest of the day the sunniest weather
will remain in scotland.
northern ireland most of england and wales
are struggling to see much in the way of brightness.
the cloud continues to fit into an occasional
patch of rain but the temperatures up patch
of rain but the temperatures up on those of
yesterday.
10- 12 degrees widely.
through tuesday evening and overnight, if
we see some gaps in this cloud sheet what
will happen is we get some fog forming and
that fog could become dense, particularly
across england and wales.
hills of the northern ireland, scotland having
clear whether an cold weather with pockets
of frost.
wednesday morning, bear in mind, if we do
see fog it has the
potential to be quite thick and it could last
while as well.
we may well see some localised disruption
through wednesday.
if you do not have fobbed you will stay cloudy
through much of the day and in any case across
england, ireland and northern -- wales and
northern ireland, a band of rain will move
into the relatively mild for most and temperatures
reaching a high of 13 degrees.
this is business briefing, i'm sally bundock.
the art of the deal.
trump's team says the us has struck $300 billion
worth of trade and investment deals during
his asian trip.
we investigate. and president trump's determination
to slash regulations for us business is alarming
many who worry about pollution and public
health.
and on the markets in asia today, shares fluctuate,
a day afterjapan’s main market saw its biggest
drop since april.