a hundred and fifty years ago hardly
anyone in Europe had ever seen a living
African elephant and then an enormous
male arrived
his name was jumbo and his story is
extraordinary and dramatic
he was rumored to be the largest
elephant on the planet and his celebrity
status took him across the globe
millions flocked to see him during his
lifetime and it said that he inspired
Hollywood movies long after his death
but contemporary accounts reveal a
troubled life fueled by alcohol with
episodes of terrifying violence a near
mystical relationship with his keeper
and a tragic end that seems hard to
believe now I'm going to look beyond
Jumbo's celebrity for the real elephant
behind the myths how big was he in
reality and what is the truth behind the
mysteries that surround his tragic death
with access to Tambor's physical remains
those questions can finally be answered
and with the help of a team of
scientists elephant experts and
conservationists I will try to find out
how our understanding of elephants has
changed since jumpers time
this is a story of the world's first
animal superstar this is the story of
jumbo
in 1882 a unique shipment is about to
arrive here in one of the busiest ports
in the world on board in a massive
wooden crate is an animal that has
already captured hearts in Britain
his name is jumbo and he's now all set
to become a superstar the most famous
animal in the world
my investigation into Jumbo's life
begins of the American Museum of Natural
History in New York there are elephant
skeletons on display here as in many
museums around the world but what I'm
looking for lies behind the scenes
Jumbos remains were brought here after
his death and are still among the most
treasured specimens in the collections
it's hard to think of a more famous
animal than jumbo I mean we have a lot
of famous specimens in the museum but
it's hard to imagine another specimen
that carries with it so much history so
much lore and legend
all these bans have been kept in the
museum's special temperature controlled
storage unit for decades unexamined but
now they're being brought out for
another look at them for the first time
in the history the museum has granted
access to Jumbo's skeleton for
scientific analysis and I'll be joining
an international team of researchers as
they attempt to answer some of the
mysteries that still surround this giant
3 one of the important things about
collections and the reason the museum
has great collections like this
including jumbo is that technologies
come about that allow you to relook at
these specimens in ways you never
imagined before among the team carrying
out this first-ever full survey of jumbo
is dr. Richard Thomas a researcher of
ancient animal bones from the University
of Leicester
with him is Professor John Hutchinson
from the Royal Veterinary College an
authority on locomotion in large land
animals finally dr. Holly Miller from
the University of Nottingham who will be
analyzing the chemical content of
Jumbo's bones tutus about his diet and
overall health
and this is what remains of jumbo
there are of course hundreds if not
thousands of elephant skeletons in
museums around the world so why should
this particular one be of special
interest
well when jumbo was alive many people
believed that he was the biggest living
land animal on earth certainly the
biggest that anyone had ever seen 20
million people came to see him and after
his death many continued to do so but
many mysteries remain exactly how big
was he and why did he have terrible fits
of rage and violence during the night
that led him to demolish the cages in
which he was kept and above all how did
he die even that is still a mystery
while the scientists across the Atlantic
begin their study of Jumbo's bones I am
looking through the archives of the
London Zoo to try and trace his story
from Africa to Britain and ultimately to
America this register records every
important event at the London Zoo and
the entry for June 26th 1865 notes the
arrival of one African elephant it was
called jumbo the name in Swahili means
hello today because of this elephant the
word jumbo has come to mean something
that's extremely large but in fact jumbo
didn't arrive as a giant far from it
the first image of him here is as a
small orphan so how did he get here
during the 19th century new zoos across
Europe and North America were looking
for spectacular exhibits that would
attract visitors
elephants were an obvious choice the
first to appear were Asian elephants
they are found in India eastwards to
Southeast Asia and as far as the
visitors to the London Zoo in Victorian
times were concerned they were the
biggest animals they had ever seen but
African elephants are much bigger in
fact they are the largest living land
animals on the planet
and unlike Asian elephants they have
hardly ever been domesticated
they were once widespread across the
continent and records suggest the Jumbo
had been captured somewhere in the
Northeast a nineteenth-century traveller
exploring the Sudan has left an account
of the brutal way in which the local
people hunted elephants they would find
a mother and a calf chased them until
they were both exhausted and then spear
the mother for death and take the baby
so young Jambo almost certainly would
have witnessed the death of his mother
hunting is still a huge problem in
Africa adults are killed for their ivory
tusks and they often leave behind young
Wasson's motherless babies just like
young jumbo as the first of his kind and
a British zoo jumbo was bound to attract
a lot of attention but his arrival
happened to coincide with a relatively
new technique called photography and
that would help to immortalize him
throughout this rich visual record of
Jumbo's life the image of one man occurs
again and again and again he was a man
whose life became totally bound up with
Jumbo's his name was Matthew Scott
Jumbo's keeper Scott was known to be a
difficult man with no close friends and
he was no expert on elephants but he did
have a deep empathy for animals of all
kinds within hours of meeting man and
beast had bonded and unusually for a
working man at the time Scott wrote an
account an autobiography of his life
with John Bell this is it there'd been
lots of books written about jumbo but
this is by far the most touching and
firsthand here's Scott describing his
first meeting with jumbo I thought I
never saw a creature so whoa be gone the
poor thing was full of disease which had
worked its way through the animals hide
and had almost eaten out its eyes Scott
now set out on his mission to raise the
young elephant it was the beginning of a
truly remarkable really
the Scot had never cared for a young
elephant before and it must have seemed
a daunting task the David Sheldrick
Wildlife Trust in Kenya knows exactly
how difficult it is head keeper Edwin
dos Ichi like Scott is caring for a new
orphan who has just arrived his elephant
close to me is called my Sierra he was
rescued from the Masai Mara
he was found stuck in the mud when he
was only about 2 month old and he seems
to have stayed there for quite some time
because he was very skinny very thin and
very weak a sign that he had been with
all the mother for quite some time and
we hope for the best for him Moo Sierra
is so traumatized by his experience a
keeper will have to stay by his side 24
hours a day
there's no quick easy fix when raising
orphaned elephants I mean you're in for
the long term so I'm arrived in
perfectly
good shape but the majority have had a
dramatic story before they get to us
the first step is straightforward
physical care but they need more than
that
elephants are highly social Monsieur ah
like jumbo needs what he would have
received from his elephant family
constant company touching and love they
need that emotional support
elephants are all about love and family
and that is what our orphans have been
robbed off and one has to very very
quickly plug that gap and it really is
the keepers at this early stage where
that strong bond is formed matthew
scott's autobiography makes it clear
that he instinctively gave jumbo the
emotional support he needed i undertook
to be his doctor his nurse and general
servant i watched a nursed him nice and
day with all the care and affection of a
mother if it were possible for a man to
do such a thing
his approach clearly worked because six
months later john bell looked like a
different elephant and could at last be
displayed to the public by the time he
was six he was beginning to carry
children on rides around the zoo and
they apparently rewarded him with sticky
buns
lots of sticky buns jumbo quickly became
hugely popular even queen victoria's
children took rides on his back but had
this once wild african elephant
really grown into a gentle giant as
Sambo grew he was moved from his stable
next to the giraffe house into a larger
enclosure but London's zoos records from
the time tell us that behind the scenes
all was not well
young bears calmness during the day was
in sharp contrast to his behavior at
night then he will become possessed by
terrifyingly violent rages in which he
would smash the Timbers of his enclosure
and he did that so regularly the
carpenters would have to be called in
again in the game in order to make
repairs and he had a curious Jekyll and
Hyde character and one that would
persist during his time in London
remarkably Matthew Scott makes no real
mention of Jumbos rages but evidence for
these violent outbursts can be readily
seen in the photos of the time
male African elephants grow the longest
of all tusks yet in nearly every photo
Jumbo's tusks seem small or even
non-existent
the head of London Zoo at the time
Abraham Bartlett has left an account of
what happened to Jumbo's tusks during
these terrifying nocturnal rages jumbo
damage not only as enclosure but himself
on one such occasion is buttered records
in his book jumbo broke both his tusks
by driving them through the iron work of
his den the tusks were broken off within
his mouth probably close to his upper
jawbone and then when they did grow
again
jumbo ground them down against the
stonework
but what could be the cause of his
nighttime outbursts and terrible acts of
self-harm may be his bones back in New
York could contain some clues
I joined Richard and John as they
examine the most impressive part of
chompers remains his huge skull one of
the first things we see when we look at
his skull
it's just how malformed his teeth are
yeah yeah I mean we can see this tooth
here is really curved in this direction
and on the other side it's curved again
so it should have been straight yeah you
wouldn't expect to see the tooth bent in
this kind of way
in a normal healthy elephant we can
think of elephant teeth a bit like
conveyor belts so they have six teeth
but only ever one of them will be in
wear on each side at any one time and
another one will be coming in underneath
and behind it to replace it at the time
which that tooth falls out when that
tooth doesn't wear down enough what
happens is it gets stuck in the mouth
and it stays there but the other tooth
carries on developing and moving up
behind it and because it's softer
because it hasn't formed properly what
happens is it hits the tooth that's
impacted and bends bends out of shape
you can see right here that was a gap
all that sweet food and other
inappropriate diet that jumbo was having
could have gotten stuck and even gotten
into the root and the gum where
infection could have got started or at
least inflammation probably pretty
painful
okay so jumbo had terrible toothache
yeah I'm afraid so
poor thing
in the wild African elephants adapt
their diet to the changing seasons
during the wet season grass can make up
90% of what they eat but in drier months
they will browse on twigs and leaves and
even bark their Ridge - teeth help grind
down this more fibrous food making it
easier to digest but what a jumbo was
his diet in captivity really as poor as
his deformed teeth suggest
dr. Holly Miller from the University of
Nottingham may help answer that by
taking samples from Jumbo's bones
particularly the femur or leg bone and
the ribs she hopes to discover more
about his diet these tiny samples could
tell us a lot about the food jumper was
eating and reveal whether or not that
affected his overall health
jumbo has some interesting stories to
tell so his femur results that gives us
the diet abroad idea of the diet for
about 20 years and the ribs a lot
shorter period of that maybe ten five to
ten years so we're seeing his diet in
London and some of his diet in America
possibly and we're seeing largely a very
stable diet in that period does that
match with a suggestion that his diet
was actually almost entirely hay and
Penny buns yes we're definitely seeing
some suggestion that he's not getting
the variety of diet that other elephants
should what they should have in their
diet is a lot of browse
they use their trunks to access the top
of trees and they get twigs and bark
which helps them you know break down the
diet the pathologies we saw with his
teeth they are coming through in the
wrong angle and they were soft they're
not hardening because they're not being
used in the right way they're not being
used to grind down the right sort of
food so it seems that elephants just
like humans can suffer severe dental
problems if they don't have the right
diet but was this having an effect on
Jumbo's behavior anyone who's had
toothache knows that it seems worse at
night when you have no distractions so
maybe this is one of the explanations
for Jumbo's terrifying nocturnal rages
and maybe too it supports the story the
Matthew Scott is keeper used to feed him
lots of whiskey in order to calm him
Scot apparently had no family or close
friends and he totally devoted himself
to jumbo even to the extent that the two
of them would often drink late into the
night but Scott's unorthodox methods to
help pacify jumbo do little to calm his
boss's nerves
Abraham Bartlet worries that instead of
attacking his cage at night jumbo by day
might turn on the public including
children as a precaution he purchases a
gun in case he has to shoot jumbo
Bartlet becomes convinced the Jumbo is
suffering not from toothache but from
must a natural condition periodically
affecting young male elephants when they
become sexually mature a Dueling must
testosterone levels in males can
increase sixty fold and they become
extremely aggressive the temporal glands
on the head behind the eyes swell and
leak and the elephants as they walk
discharge an almost continuous dribble
of urine creating a scent trail until
recently there was little research on
young male elephants dr. Vickie fish
lock is one of a team of researchers
who've been studying males in Kenya's
Amboseli National Park and she's now
beginning to understand what drives
their behavior was Abraham Bartlet write
about must being the cause of jumpers
aggression
so males in lost are really signaling
their competitive ability they're really
signaling that they're in great shape
and that females shouldn't meet with
them and other males should look out
must is really a way of saying I'm here
I'm big and I'm on a mission I usually
say they're cruising for girls and
trouble in the wild must usually starts
when a male elephant is in his mid to
late 20s but in captivity must can begin
much earlier and indeed jumbo was 21
when his nitrate is intensified could
his frightened aggression come from must
Vickie is not convinced must is really
for elephants a state about dominance
and establishing dominance
so if Jumbo's rages had been associated
with musk you would expect that would be
to direct it not just to his physical
surrounding but to his keepers as well
who were also controlling his behavior
in some way so you would expect him to
have directed some aggression towards
the humans around him but there is
nothing in the historical records to
suggest that jumper was ever violent
towards people so was Abraham Bart
mistaken for blaming Jumbo's increasing
aggression on must could there perhaps
be another explanation
work in the United States with retired
zoo and circus elephants may provide the
answer Sukie track here the behavioral
problems had afflicted Jambo more than a
hundred years ago are all too familiar
to carers who work with the African
elephants here in the elephant sanctuary
in Tennessee
the sanctuary is created to provide a
home for old or unwanted elephants
across America the elephants themselves
have been captured as orphans in Africa
and then kept isolated or locked up like
Jambo
when they first arrived here many are
extremely agitated and aggressive an
evidence of self-harm is all too obvious
their tusks worn down by repeated
rubbing against their den walls the
similarities the jambo are clear but
there is one big difference these
elephants are all female so clearly
they're ggressive nests cannot be due to
a surge of male hormones in fact their
behaviour quickly improves as they
settle in and build friendships with
other elephants in the sanctuary we now
know that elephants are extremely social
animals they need the company of their
own kind and we also know that they're
extremely intelligent they easily get
bored so keeping a single elephant in
captivity is not a way to rear a happy
and healthy elephant
to visitors to London Zoo in the 19th
century
Jambo did indeed appear to be a happy
elephant but they had no idea of his
aggressive darker side Bartlett kept
that a secret and back at the Museum in
New York there is evidence that his life
in captivity was also damaging his
physical health when we look at the knee
we see all sorts of kind of changes in
the bone we wouldn't really expect
seeing an elephant of his age remember
jumbo is only twenty four and still
growing but what we see actually when we
start looking at the bone surface we can
see it's really Ruffin and you'll see
these extra lumps of bone that shouldn't
be there we've got on this side and
John's got them on at the side of the
tibia yeah there's some bumps invading
into the joint surface itself which is
not a good sign and what these are is
these are lumps of bone at the point
where ligaments are attaching to the
joints and the bone is adapting to try
and compensate for all those stresses
he's experiencing for a 24 year old
elephant it's kind of like a 24 year old
person having similar kinds of joint
problems well we know jumbo carried
loads of people certainly children I
think even a doze could that have
produced this consequence
sure yeah loading them up with people
and walking them around on a hard
surface and not giving them the right
diet all these factors could spiral
together and give jumbo problems like
these joint information problems so far
from being bad tempered with these
nocturnal rages sounds as though is
extraordinarily patient day after day
after day two to carry passengers which
is what the zoo did
there is no doubt that jumbo was held in
deep affection by the general public but
his bones suggest that he was in effect
being harmed by those who were toward
him most the stresses and strains of
captivity combined with a poor diet and
hundreds of rides at London Zoo created
symptoms usually associated with old age
his bones are more like an elephant in
its forties or fifties than in stretches
there's nothing in the zoo's records
suggesting that they had concerns about
Jumbo's health but the head of the zoo
Abraham Bartlett was still extremely
worried about Jumbo's fits of
uncontrollable violence as a result he
makes a shocking decision to try and
sell the popular elephant and he hears
of a possible buyer the famous American
circus showman PT Barnum news that
Barnum was looking for an African
elephant reach the London Zoo in the
form of a telegram which said what was
the lowest price that they would accept
for their African elephant here was a
marvelous opportunity for barter to get
rid of his problematic elephant and he
cabled back 2,000 pounds that's over a
hundred and fifty thousand pounds in
today's money an enormous sum and this
register shows that it was accepted
PT Barnum was the owner of the popular
greatest show on earth turning circus
which already featured 20 a chanel
offense he was an astute businessman who
had made his fortune exhibiting fake
curiosities and he wanted a star
attraction to draw in crowds to his new
circus Barnum sent his head elephant
keeper to collect jumbo and we know how
difficult a task that proved to be
because newspapers at the time reported
in detail on this highly public event as
crowds gathered he attached chains
around the elephant's neck jumbo ripped
them off they attached more change than
the venturi got him to the mouth of the
crate whereupon jumbo sensing a trap
simply lowered himself onto his stomach
and sat there and nothing anybody could
do were make him budge
both Bartlett and Barnum began to
suspect that his keeper Scott was using
some form of secret language with Jambo
to make him unwilling to leave the zoo
could that be possible
good man an elephant have talked to each
other today we know that elephants use a
variety of ways to communicate but it's
taken decades of field research to
decode the many sounds and signals that
they use despite having poor eyesight
elephants will use visual signals to
communicate when near each other their
ears trunks and tails can all be used to
indicate emotional moods come on okay Oh
in recent years scientists have come to
discover that elephants are even able to
understand the gesture that we tend to
think of is uniquely human pointing not
only that it's been shown that they can
distinguish between different human
voices so was Matthew Scott secretly
telling jumbo to stay put I'm absolutely
sure that in a situation where you have
a one-on-one relationship like jumbo had
with his keeper the trust that gets
built up enables two-way communication
and what happens next
seems to support this Barnum offered to
take on Scott as jumpers keeper to go
with his beloved elephant to America and
almost immediately after this deal is
agreed Jambo cooperated
as the frenzy about Jumbo's departure
reaches its peak 20,000 people a day
assembled at the zoo to protest about it
a court case was filed to try and
prevent the bargain Queen Victoria was
said to be extremely upset but the deal
had been done on the 22nd of March 1882
in the middle of the night crowds of
onlookers assembled to watch jumbo being
pulled to the docks by 12 horses with
Scott standing stroking his elephant's
trunk in reassurance
jumbo arrived at 5 o'clock in the
morning down here some Katharine's dock
he was loaded onto a barge and then
taken out to the assyrian monarch the
british ship that was going to take him
across the atlantic he drank some beer
followed by a whiskey chaser and then
the world's most famous elephant was
ready for his departure as the ship
slowly sailed down the Thames thousands
lined its banks to wish him well the
publicity surrounding his departure had
not gone unnoticed on the other side of
the Atlantic and would ensure that a
huge crowd would be waiting to receive
him
it was a two-week journey across the
ocean to New York City and it must have
been a horrible trip for the animal it
seems that at times he was a little
seasick and had to be kept calm with
alcohol but over in America jumbo mania
was already erupting and his new owner
PT Barnum was keen to fuel this
excitement when the Assyrian Manik
reached the Hudson River
Barnum chartered a small boat to take
him out to the ship so that he could see
his purchase for the very first time was
it really as big as he had hoped
Barnum declared without hesitation that
this was the biggest African elephant in
the world whether that was true or not
to discover how a big jumbo really was
we can turn to his bones again the team
will use his leg bone as a starting
point so one of the things we can do is
we can take the femur so we can take the
like this brush this boat yeah and we
can measure the length because this is
the bone that is the longest bone in the
elephant's body and it gives us a good
indication of how tall jumbo might have
been so how long was it 107 centimeters
circumference is 39 centimeters we can
estimate his weight at around 6,000
kilograms that's not jumbo is measuring
in 3.2 meters tall and we know how old
he was and we know how old he is and
that's really really important we know
he's 24 at the time of his death what we
can establish is what a normal wild
African elephant
should be at shoulder height at that age
and that would be about 2.7 meters so
3.2 meters actually that's 20 percent
different doesn't it almost different
you have a jumbo was was taller than he
should be for his age
wow that's surprised jumbo is about 20
percent taller yeah 3.2 meters is what
he really was at the shoulder and
instead what he should have been for a
wild African elephant at 24 years of age
would be more like 2.7 yeah so he's he's
a leggy elephant firs age so Jumbo's
height was around 10 feet 6 inches or
3.2 meters at the time of his death
evidence from wild elephants suggests
that they can reach up to 13 feet or 4
meters in height and will weigh almost
7,000 kilograms
but his leg bone tells us more this
zigzag line here this crack tells us I
assumed that he was still going yes
absolutely right so the ends of the bone
are separate from the main body of the
bone when mammals are growing and
eventually they will unite when the
animal reaches its full size but we can
see here because this crack is still
open we can see that jumbo is still
growing male African elephants continue
to grow until they're 40
so jumbo had another 16 years of growing
so although he wasn't quite as tall as
Barnum said he was this animal had the
potential of being exceptionally big he
could have been a record breaker if he
had had that 16 extra years to grow
Jumbo's leg shows us that he was indeed
a very big elephant in fact he was
bigger than you would expect for an
elephant of his age he wasn't as big as
Barnum claimed but he was still growing
and he could have actually matched that
claim had he lived
but then as jumbo tours North America
with the circus there is a major change
with 20 other elephants to keep him
company
jumbo has a lot more stimulation and
there are no accounts of the night rages
he suffered in London and of course
Matthew Scott his keeper from London Zoo
is by his side throughout but what about
Jumbo's health at this time the research
team has another fine to show me a
rather gruesome piece of Jumbo's remains
so this rather extraordinary relic is
actually Jumbo's tail it's actually a
really key part of the Jumbo puzzle from
Tufts University in Massachusetts where
they held jumbo stuffed body after he
died but unfortunately that was lost in
a fire but we still have the remarkable
tale and what we have is these hairs
some very thick and some very thin the
thinner ones are new growth we can take
some samples of these finer hairs and
one of the thicker longer growing hairs
so we get a nice snapshot of Jumbo's
diet almost right before he died who
would have thought it well Holly
analyzes the chemical content of Jumbo's
tail Richard and John discovers
something unusual about Jumbo's hip bone
it's both sides and it's also the same
layering effects you've got the sort of
older remodeled bone underneath and
you've got this layer of active new bone
forming on top really really very
pronounced a lot of information
he's got so many signs of stress and
strain related injuries there must've
been incredibly painful for him but may
have reflected that there used to which
he was put both in London and in a
circus in America could these science of
information indicate the Jumbos health
was in serious decline Holly has now had
time to look at the chemical clues in
the hair samples from Jumbo's tail and
of particular interest is the amount of
nitrogen an element that's crucial to
the repair of the body
Jumbo's nitrogen values are odd when
compared to other elephants in other
circumstances and we can see that jumbo
is the highest of all these here our
line is by quite a long way yes
so elephants can reach these levels when
they're stressed but it only happened
seasonally when they're not getting much
from their diet you see stress that
doesn't mean the stress on the body
means something to do with the diet
physiologically stress their bodies
aren't getting necessarily what they
need from their environment and if we
think about what we saw where he was
laying down all that new bone in his
pelvis to create new bone in your body
you need an awful lot of protein so he
would have been taking all of that from
his diet
he's also we think at the end probably
quite sick we have some written records
that suggests that he was unwell towards
the end with some sort of wasting
disease potentially
Jumbo's body must have been trying
desperately to extract as much nitrogen
as it could from his diet to help repair
the bone in his hip these injuries were
likely related to his treatment in
captivity and it seems that as a result
jumbo was losing weight there is little
doubt that he must have been suffering
but that didn't stop his American owner
PT Barnum from finding new ways to
promote his biggest elephant and a
remarkable opportunity soon arose
the Brooklyn Bridge is one of the oldest
suspension bridges in the United States
it was in fact opened in 1883 the year
after jumbo arrived in America and
almost immediately an accident on it led
to the death of 12 people so to squash
any rumors about the bridges safety the
authorities agreed to an unusual
publicity stunt
on the 17th of May 1884 thousands of
people lined these banks to see 20
elephants led by John Doe
marching across the bridge what a sight
it must have been scotch
Jumbo's Kiefer was nervous about the
whole event this is what he writes about
it when jumbo put his foot down on the
bridge the bridge rebounded after the
shock given by his foot the rebound was
made by his second footstep and there
was a great vibration caused by it
I assure my reader that I was thankful
when we arrived on the bottle inside
although jumbo goes back to touring with
the rest of the circus all is not well
it seems the bone damage to jumpers leg
is becoming a problem in his day-to-day
life not long after the parade across
Brooklyn Bridge an associate of Barnum's
reports in a letter than an ailing jumbo
could no longer lie down that doesn't
stop Barnum who's keen to keep the
circus traveling with his prized
elephant
in September 1885 the circus train
crosses the border into Canada on what
should be a routine tour
I'm keen to follow their journey
because the accounts of what happened
next are shocking and tragic in the
1880s st. Thomas Ontario is the perfect
stop for Barnum & Bailey Circus it's the
central hub for 26 different railways
that converged here from all over North
America on the day when the circus comes
to town jumbo is once again the main
attraction drawing crowds from miles
around
by the late evening the show is over the
tents are being taken down the
performers are packing up and the
animals are being led down to the Train
jumbo and a small elephant called Tom
Thumb are the last to be loaded and as
Matthew Scott leads them towards their
boxcar a freight train comes thundering
down the track towards them reports of
what happens next
differ some eyewitness accounts record
jumbo running away from the Train
but soon after Barnum claims the
opposite he declares Jumbo's death a
great heroic act telling reporters that
the large elephant had run headfirst
into the Train sacrificing his own life
to save his keeper and Tom Thumb the
smaller elephant this image based on
Barnum's account of Jumbo's head-on
crash was to be published again and
again
so what is the truth what actually
happened on that railroad in San Thomas
the research team has been looking over
Jumbo's bones for signs of injury now
that you've seen the entire skeleton is
there anything we can deduce about the
way in which he met his end is there our
first thought was we might find some
evidence of trauma in a skeleton that
might relate to the impact of the train
accident so we've looked at the skeleton
for evidence of fractures and we have
found no signs of any bone fractures
that are affected either his skull or
his pelvis amazing so the exact details
of jumpers death are still rather
puzzling while the rest of the world may
have forgotten Jumbos story in the town
where he died it's a proud part of their
history the elgin county museum is
almost a shrine to Jumbos memory and I'm
hoping it's curator Mike Baker will have
some clues to help explain exactly how
jumbo died this group of things that
were found in his stomach while the skin
and the bones are being prepared for
mounting there's a little miniature Pig
at the back which is actually a match
safe a charm bracelet a button a collar
stud and a tooth I don't want to think
about how he got a tooth but they're all
part of the many many things they found
in jumbled stomach including quite a few
coins clenched yes maybe as many as 300
mostly pennies pennies that I think were
supposed to have gone to Scott this
payment for a ride and then not quite
making it to Scott
jumbo would have grabbed him with his
trunk because I think it was a bit of a
kleptomaniac with that trunk and these
what are these well these appear to be
photographs of the locomotive that
collided with him the very one that
brought about his death yeah not too
many years later and the most
interesting feature is the little tin
elephant
that someone has cut out say yes this is
the locomotive that got jumbled yeah I'm
so sure why they're proud of that but
they were keen to market anyway among
all this memorabilia is a photograph
taken just after Jumbo's death
this is a much enlarged version of the
photo that you often see a poor dead
jumble it's taken about a day after the
accident it's Scott at his head and one
of the owners of the circus Hutchison
lying against them and it's interesting
to see in this photograph now that's
blowing up you can see a series of
abrasions on his height and it matches
up very nicely with the one good graphic
from soon after the collision mike has
come across an image of jumbo that I've
not seen before it was discovered in an
antique print gallery in Washington and
is now on loan to the museum and it is
the final piece of the Jumbo jigsaw it's
probably the best depiction of the
actual collision with jumbo this was
done by an artist possibly on the site
about three days after the collision it
matches very nicely with the
photographic evidence and you can see
the engine coming up behind jumbo so
causing the abrasions that you can see
in the enlarged photograph it's the same
point of contact so here is Matthew
Scott having failed to signal to the
locomotive that is the circus train with
the boxcar the Jumbo was going to get
into and the locomotive was outrun him
and hit him in the rear and that's the
end of poor jumbo exactly not what
Barnum said no not at all
so Barnum saw was a complete invention
pure Buncombe as as he would probably
say
with no evidence of fractures on Jumbo's
bones it seems the most likely cause of
death was internal bleeding so it's
unlikely that jumbo died instantly
giving Scott time to say goodbye to his
much-loved elephant
eyewitness accounts report that Scott
rushed to Jumbo's side and watched as he
took one last breath and died his
devoted keeper is said to have wept
inconsolably at the loss of his best
friend Matthew Scott never really
recovered from the death of his beloved
elephant he hung around the surface for
some time and then Barnum in a
businesslike and brisk way paid him off
and had Jumbo's body stuffed and mounted
and paraded jumbo was just 24 when he
died
his death became front-page news around
the world
the young elephant who had arrived at
London's sewers and orphan had become a
hugely popular and much-loved superstar
he gave a great number of people
enormous pleasure and a vivid
unforgettable impression of the
magnificence of the natural world that
lay far beyond European cities but we
now know that the life he led was not
the right life for an elephants keeping
elephants locked up on their own goes
against everything that they've evolved
to be not having any choice not having
anything different would be really
detrimental to their well-being just
like it's bad for people
in the case of jumbo I didn't think
there's anything worse than
incarceration announcement a really
really tragic life lost
maybe it's remarkable he survived as
long as he did in the conditions that
elephants were kept in at the time
because no one really knew how to care
for an African elephant there were still
mysterious exotic animals from deepest
darkest Africa we do have the choice of
how we take care of elephants wherever
they are and jumbo is a good case of
where we did not take good care of an
elephant and we can learn from that
thankfully we now have a much deeper
understanding of the needs of elephants
we've come to realize that they should
always be in the company of their own
kind so that they can build lasting
relationships and they need space to
live their lives but many held in
captivity today do not have that space
one hundred and thirty years after jumbo
was killed there's good news
circuses across Europe and America are
sending their performing elephants into
retirement
of course the elephants can't be
returned to the wild they were captured
too young to have learnt the skills
necessary to survive out there but
thankfully there are sanctuaries like
this one in Tennessee
here there are great areas of woodland
where the elephant can roam and do what
they want to do and not what human
beings tell them to do
young bears life was cut cruelly short
but these elephants will have a chance
of having a long and peaceful end to
theirs
forget all the cold and snow here today
and savor an exotic adventure in Havana
Cuba with the real marigold on tour
tomorrow at 9:00 here on BBC one